This is our galaxy.
This is our planet.
And this is the story of mankind.
[music] 5,000 years ago, planet Earth
would be home to the first human
civilizations. [music]
Humans from across the world would be in
a race for survival, meaning, [music]
and power. Their
small cities [music]
transformed into advanced civilizations
around the globe. People formed unique
cultures similar in humanity yet
different in expression.
But soon civilizations became so
advanced they would ascend from survival
to world domination.
And now you're here. This is the story
of all that happened before you.
[music]
>> [music]
>> 150,000 years ago, we took our first
steps.
Hunter gatherer civilizations endured in
harsh loces ranging from the Arctic
tundra
to the Amazon rainforest.
Here, primitive peoples began wielding
fire to reshape [music] their world.
Hunter gatherers roame the earth for
more than 100,000 years.
All throughout the world, primitive
humans slowly began to express
themselves. Their mastery of stone tools
allowed early humans to ascend the food
chain and become Earth's dominant
predator.
This, however, was not our destiny.
In the fertile plains of the Middle
East, the first farmers would scatter
seeds into the ground. They mastered the
delicate dance of planting, harvesting,
and nurturing, transforming their once
wild surroundings into a thriving oasis
of crops.
Society begins to emerge.
Not long after, we begin domesticating
animals.
We could stay exactly where we were and
let food come to us.
All throughout the world, clutches of
mud huts became primitive cities.
This was a revolution.
Sumeriia was the world's first known
civilization.
Its early cities emerged in Mesopotamia
over 7,000 years ago between the Tigris
and Euphrates rivers.
Uruk was the first city beginning as
early as 5,000 BC.
The Samrians gave humanity one of the
greatest inventions in history. Hunia
was born, the world's first [music]
writing system. For the first time ever,
humans could share knowledge across any
distance, time, and generation.
Sumerian blacksmiths began melting their
ordinary rocks of copper and tin
together. The result was bronze.
Tools and weapons that were once weak
and brittle were now stronger and more
durable.
The Stone Age was now over. The Bronze
Age had begun. Equipped with a bronze
sword and shields, humans fought across
Mesopotamia, waging brutal wars to
conquer neighboring cities.
But war was only one part of ancient
life. Other people would begin to
advance architecture [music]
and building. Over 4,000 years ago, the
Samrians built the legendary ziggurats,
extraordinary temple monuments still
standing tall to this day.
The Samrians will mark the birth of
civilization
[music]
in the land of Egypt. A new
architectural experiment was taking
place in 2650 BC. The pyramid
Egyptian civilization flourished along
the Nile River for thousands of years.
They had a structured society. At the
bottom, millions of peasants, workers,
and slaves. At the top, the pinnacle of
human existence, the Pharaoh. The people
worshiped the Pharaoh, believing it was
them who were responsible for the River
Nile's fertile soil. The Egyptians
created hieroglyphs, their own intricate
writing system that we still understand
today.
Believing in an afterlife, they began
mummifying people and animals. so their
spirits would continue to live on. Under
Pharaoh Joseer, the kingdom expanded to
the largest and most powerful the world
had ever seen. To mark his legendary
rule, Joser wanted a great royal tomb.
He had just the idea, the step pyramid,
a building which would reflect the
pharaoh's position at the pinnacle of
human existence.
It was decorated with stunning white
limestone rising over 60 m into the
desert sky. After his death, Jose's
mummified remains lay inside this
magnificent structure. The age of
pyramids had begun.
Taking power in 2613 BC, the great
pharaoh took pyramid building to another
level.
During his 27-year reign, he constructed
the Maidum pyramid, the bent pyramid,
and the Red Pyramid.
Sniferu was succeeded by his son, Kufu.
He was no great leader. Seeing that he
could never live up to his father as a
ruler, Kufu insisted to triumph his
glory. He began to work on the greatest
[music] monument of the ancient world.
The Great Pyramid of Giza was born. It
would soon stand at [music] a massive
481 ft, the tallest building in the
world until 1889 AD, over [music] 4,500
years later.
And finally, the Great Sphinx would be
constructed to protect the sacred sites
of the Giza pyramids.
Egypt had become the world's first great
superpower.
[music]
Since 4500 BC, the land of China would
see early settlements along the Yellow
River in the [music] north and the Yang
Sea in the south. The people lived
agricultural lifestyles, growing millet
and rice residing on the flood plains.
However, they were plagued by the great
flood, [music] a natural disaster
constantly washing away their crops and
killing settlers. The founding of
China's first dynasty began with Yu, the
man who built a legendary canal system
to bring an end to the flood. Tribal
leaders throughout the land named Yu
their successor, and in 270 BC, the Sha
dynasty was founded. The lands of China
would have their first king, Yu, and the
people thrived in their new society. For
centuries, the Shia ruled a stable
Chinese state of over 2 million
citizens.
But after nearly 500 years, the Sha were
conquered by their neighbors in the
north, the Shang dynasty. The wars were
brutal and [music] marked something more
than the fall of one dynasty. The Shang
brought China into the Bronze Age.
Bronze tools were stronger and would
last longer. And soon the Shing would
pioneer remarkable horsedrawn chariots,
wielding skilled archers who could fire
their bows while moving [music] across
the battlefield.
China had now become part of humanity's
first era of truly advanced
civilizations.
Back in Mesopotamia, the small city of
Babylon had become a rising power.
[music]
In 1792 BC, the legendary King Hammurabi
turned the small Babylonian citystate
into an empire.
Hemarabi would remarkably conquer
Sumerian cities, Ashuna or Aruk [music]
and the city of Ashore in the east.
Hemarabi was not just a fierce warrior.
He was also a brilliant statesman.
Having achieved its territorial aims,
Hammurabi issued his legendary law code
in 1755 BC. For the first time in human
history, a civilization had inscribed
hundreds of laws on a large stone steel.
The code of Hammurabi. It contains 282
laws and their punishments if broken.
The saying an eye for an eye comes from
this code as there was a written law
that blinding another citizen will be
punished by removal of the eyes. Another
written law says if a son struck his
father, his hands would be cut off.
Showing that to the Babylonians, respect
for parents was sacred. Marriage too was
held sacred with one law stating if a
married woman was caught committing
adultery, [music]
both she and the man would be tied
together and thrown into the Euphrates
River. Despite its ancient brutality,
these laws helped the Babylonians become
an advanced civilization. But they were
no warriors. This was the Bronze Age
after all, and force was the deciding
factor. And so Hammurabi's empire did
not outlive him by long.
[music]
Europe's earliest civilization emerged
around 2000 BC. Isolated on the small
lush island of Cree, the Manoan people
were developing a sophisticated society
of their own.
They were the first ever to build ships
that would connect European civilization
with the rest of [music] the world. They
set sail, establishing trading posts
throughout the Mediterranean, becoming
one of the richest powers of their time.
In a legendary voyage, they even made
their way to the kingdoms of Egypt,
where merchants with different languages
learned to trade together, beginning
international commerce that would last
for centuries.
Soon their capital city of Nosis was
filled with magnificent palaces spanning
an incredible 45 acres. The Manoans even
had flushing toilets, an innovation that
wouldn't become widespread in Europe
again until the Romans more than 1,000
years later. Nasus remains the first
known advanced city in Europe, and its
ruins are still standing after 3,500
years. But their own writing system,
linear A, still hasn't been deciphered
by archaeologists.
NSUS was damaged by an earthquake in
1700 BC and was rebuilt on an even
grander scale, surviving for another 500
years. However, nature was unforgiving.
In 1500 BC, a massive volcano erupted in
nearby the severely disrupting Manoan
trade. Just 50 years later, a
devastating earthquake struck Cree. And
while she was weakened, a full-scale
invasion from her Greek neighbors
followed. The Manowans simply couldn't
survive such a series of disasters. And
in 1450 BC, their civilization collapsed
entirely.
[music]
In the vast Pacific Ocean, some of
humanity's most masterful seafarers were
adventuring to unknown lands.
In 1600 BC, early Austronesian peoples
in Taiwan traveled 5,000 m by deep ocean
canoe to reach the Isisles of Polynia.
It is perhaps mankind's most daring
expedition.
They had no compasses, no maps. Early
Polynesian explorers navigated by the
patterns in the swells, the species of
birds flying overhead, and most
importantly, the [music] stars. Through
unceasing lifelong observation, they
learned the exact pattern of the stars
as they [music] rise and fall, and how
this varied from season to season. They
could thus choose a specific star or
series of stars by which to navigate.
For their efforts, they were rewarded.
They found lush uninhabited islands.
Fiji, Tonga, Samoa.
Here, the daring colonists created
vibrant new civilizations.
They built massive homes perched on
stilts to withstand the tempestuous
elements
and sustained themselves on the fruits
of the sea.
Over time, a unique culture emerged.
Using razor-sharp obsidian blades, they
covered their bodies in winding, [music]
intricate tattoos,
undisturbed and isolated in the Pacific,
these civilizations thrived for
millennia. They may not have constructed
great works, but they remain some of the
most stable and enduring cultures in
mankind's history.
But in Egypt, a crisis was unfolding.
A series of weak-willed rulers had
allowed the kingdom to descend into
chaos.
By 1650 BC, Egypt had fallen under
foreign rule for the first time in its
3,000-year history.
The Hixos, [music] fearsome nomadic
peoples from the Levant. They had seized
their opportunity and now occupied all
of lower Egypt. In the south, the
ancient dynasty of thieves still
reigned, but the situation was
deteriorating. In 1570 BC, the rightful
pharaoh was killed in battle with the
Hixos. Power fell to his son, Amos I,
only 10 years old. The boy king watched
helplessly as not just his father but
also his elder brother was slain by the
Hixos. Just like that, he had become the
end of the royal line.
And yet his forces were simply too weak,
too scattered. For 20 years, Amos abided
his time, letting his hated foes occupy
his homeland. The fate of the kingdom
lay in the young man's development. The
Egyptian people held their breath.
When Amos came of age and his regency
ended, it was clear he had become
exactly the ruler Egypt needed.
Strong, intelligent, ambitious, and on
an unstoppable quest for revenge, his
countrymen gathered around him, and in
the 20th year of his reign, he
personally led the charge.
He drove the Hixos out of Egypt, chased
them back to the Levant, and sacked
their capital of Shah Ruhen. Amuse
avenged [music] his fallen family
members, liberated his people and
unified Egypt once more.
He ushered in a second golden age. The
new kingdom was born. Rather than
constructing massive pyramids, [music]
new kingdom pharaohs would be laid to
rest in rock tombs cut directly into the
earth. miles of secret chambers designed
to confuse grave robbers. Their tombs
were riddled with deadend corridors and
trap doors, hiding precious artifacts
and secret knowledge for 3,500 years.
That is until 1922 with the discovery of
Toutin Common's tomb. Inside they found
thousands of treasures, including his
coffin made of [music] solid gold and
Tuten Common's own death mask, the most
famous artifact on the planet.
undoubtedly worth billions of dollars.
It was in the New Kingdom that the Ebers
Papyrus was written, one of the world's
oldest surviving medical books.
Thousands of years ahead of their time,
the Papyrus recognized mental conditions
such as depression, anxiety, and
dementia in the same manner as physical
medical conditions, encouraging doctors
to help rather than simply punishing or
blaming the gods.
Egypt had risen to the height of its
civilization.
In Greece, a similar unification was
taking place. A fierce warrior
civilization ruled the Isisles.
The Masonans.
Like the Manowans, their society
centered around great palaces, vast and
impenetrable fortresses sprinkled
throughout Greece. Unlike the Manoans,
the Masonans were conquerors.
In 1600 B.CE, they took their first
steps toward expansion. Within 200
years, they controlled all of Greece.
The Masonans were no expert merchants,
however. Instead, their society was
built around military hierarchy and
conquering lands. Their soldiers were
the first in Europe to wear full body
armor, the Dendra Ponopoly from the
1400s BC. This set covered the entire
body with bronze plates. Less soldiers
would die, leaving more to defend their
new kingdoms.
They buried their most accomplished
kings with gold death masks. The most
famous being the mask of Agamemnon
discovered in 1876.
For 500 years, the Masonans raised havoc
and reigned supreme in the Greek isles.
By the turn of the millennium, however,
their days were numbered by a mysterious
collapse. Their kingdoms and conquest
would inspire future Greek stories and
legends that fascinate [music] the
entire world to this day.
Under the Masonans, the worldrenowned 12
gods of Olympus began to emerge.
Mythical figures guiding every aspect of
Greek life. Tales of the Greek gods are
riddled with jealousy, betrayal, and
intrigue. Today, we read these tales as
epic stories, but for the ancient
Greeks, this was their religion. beliefs
that shaped their entire lives and
civilization.
For example, before setting sail,
sailors would pray to Poseidon,
believing it was him who controlled the
storms and the seas.
Even before a battle, the Greek armies
would sacrifice their livestock, hoping
the gods Aries and Athena would grant
them military victory in return.
These gods held such a major part in
Greek society that grand construction
projects were built in dedication to
them. The temple of Zeus in Olympia
would house one of the seven wonders of
the ancient world. The statue [music] of
Zeus made of golden ivory. The statue
stood 13 m high and took 13 years to
complete and would stand tall [music]
for the next thousand years.
The most famous though was the Parthonon
built for the goddess Athenia.
Constructed almost 2500 years ago
entirely from marble, it remains one of
the greatest architectural achievements
of the ancient world. No matter where
you go in Athens today, you can see the
architectural wonder as it sits upon the
Athenian Acropolis Hill overlooking the
entire [music] city.
>> [music]
>> The subcontinent of India had seen the
unique Indis Valley civilization
flourish from the year 3,300 BC. A
collection of cities along the Indis
River, these peoples had mastered water
infrastructure and sewage systems that
would not be matched elsewhere in the
world for another thousand years. In
their largest city, Mohenjjo Daro, they
created the world's first advanced
toilets built with a seed in a chute
that led to the underground drainage
[music] system.
But with the collapse of the Indis
Valley civilization, a dark age reigned
on the Indian subcontinent. In 1500 BC,
a new light emerged. The Veta,
a series of religious texts whose
worship was believed to maintain harmony
between humans and the universe.
The Vadic peoples migrated to India from
Iran in 1500 BC. They conquered swiftly.
They were fearsome warriors.
The Vadics reign supreme on the
subcontinent.
Vadic religious practice would form the
basis of Hinduism and Vadic teachings
gave India its cast system the social
pyramid of India. At the top
representing the head were the priestly
class responsible for studying,
understanding and educating on religious
texts. Below them representing the hands
and arms were mainly warriors but also
included kings, nobles [music] and even
administrators. For the thighs, we have
the landowning farmers, merchants, and
businessmen. And finally, at the feet of
the cast system were laborers, and
peasants. Their job was to serve the
other three classes.
This cast system would endure for over
3,000 years.
Over [music]
centuries, the Hittite peoples built one
of the most powerful empires in the
Bronze Age. Founded in central Turkey in
1700 BC, the Hittite Kingdom expanded
aggressively. At their peak, they
reached the Black Sea in the north and
Syria in the south. They mastered
archery on the back of horse chariots,
becoming one of the strongest militaries
of their time. Their chief deity,
Teshub, was the god of storms and
epitomizes their explosive, vengeful
military lifestyle. They were so
powerful that royals from the Hittite
kingdom would even marry Egyptian queens
and pharaohs, using marriage as an
international political tool. Peaceful
coexistence between these two ancient
superpowers was not to be, however. The
two would face off in the most well
doumented battle in ancient history.
The battle took place in May of 1274 BC
with Ramsy's the great leading his
troops to seize the Hittite city of
Kadesh.
On the side of the Egyptians, 20,000
troops. For the Hittites, [music] 50,000
troops.
Over 15,000 total charioteers were
present and to this day it is the
largest battle involving chariots ever
fought. The Hittites smashed into the
stunned Egyptian infantry entirely
[music]
routing their forces and even reaching
the Egyptian camp. The Egyptian troops
rallied and launched a counterattack.
The Hittites were driven back into the
river where many drowned. Unable to
carry out a long siege, Ramsay's
returned to Egypt. He claimed absolute
victory, stating that he had never
intended to take Kadesh and that the
battle was a personal triumph. The
Hittite king also claimed victory in the
battle, stating that he had turned away
Ramsay's approach. In reality, neither
of these superpowers could defeat the
other outright. Soon, this stalemate
would be codified. The Treaty of Kadesh,
it promised [music] everlasting peace
and brotherhood between the two
kingdoms. It is the only surviving peace
treaty from the ancient world and the
birth of international law.
Yet within a century, both kingdoms
would face a catastrophe far greater
than war. One that would consume the
entire ancient world.
[music]
In 1110 BC, a perfect storm was brewing.
Crippling drought in the Middle East and
Egypt. A massive eruption bringing years
of volcanic winter throughout the
Mediterranean. Food shortages were
rampant and people all over were growing
desperate. Soon it came, the downfall of
civilization,
the Sea Peoples.
[music]
fearsome tribal warriors from lands
shrouded in mystery still unknown to
this day. Traveling the seas on fast,
versatile ships. What began as coastal
raids quickly became full-scale
invasion. In 1180 BC, the Hittite Empire
collapsed entirely. 5 years later, the
Masonian and Matani kingdoms followed,
plunging Greece into a centuries long
dark age. The Egyptians were the only
civilization in the ancient world able
to defend themselves from the sea
peoples and managed to survive the
environmental disasters of the 1100s. It
was what felt like the end of the world.
With almost all of the Bronze Age
civilizations completely destroyed, the
start of a new era dawned upon humanity,
the Iron Age.
Peoples across the world began melting
ordinary rocks in blazing furnaces. The
result was iron.
Tools and weapons that were once jagged
and fragile were now sharper and
tougher.
With this new innovation, civilizations
would soon be built greater than ever
before.
For centuries, the Joe tribe lived under
the yoke of their militaristic Shang
overlords. In 1050 BC, however, the
Shang king went too far. After the
leader of the Joe tribe successfully
conquered a massive stretch of territory
on behalf of the king, he and his family
were invited to the capital on the
pretense of reward. When they arrived,
they were immediately arrested. The
tribe leader was sentenced to death. His
children managed to escape imprisonment
and fled to their home. Determined to
avenge their father's betrayal, they
marched on the Shang with 45,000 men.
The king met them with 170,000. At the
Battle of Muya in 1046 BC, the
outnumbered Joe forces crushed the Shang
army. The Shang King, seeing he was
ruined, committed suicide by burning
himself alive.
Thus began Joe's 700year reign in China,
which would see the most fundamental
aspects of Chinese culture fall into
place. The Zhao introduced a feudal
system, but the emperor giving power to
nobles to rule local lands.
Governing a vast empire was now easier
for the Chinese emperor. But over time,
those same nobles became powerful enough
to challenge the king himself.
In came one of history's most powerful
political ideas, the mandate of heaven.
For the first time, an emperor's right
to govern was no longer seen as
absolute. It depended on justice,
wisdom, and the will of heaven itself.
In simple terms, a cruel or corrupt king
would lose his throne. For the next
2,000 years, the mandate of heaven would
decide who ruled China and who didn't.
The Zhao would enter the Iron Age and
were soon able to mass-produce iron in
unbelievable quantities.
The Iron Jean, a remarkable double-edged
sword, would be crafted for the most
elite Joe soldiers. Then came the Joe's
greatest military innovation, the
crossbow. Instead of drawing and
releasing the bow string by hand, this
bow's act of firing was like a
modern-day gun. Aim, then simply squeeze
a trigger. But the Chinese didn't just
change their hierarchy and weaponry. A
new philosophical idea emerged known by
the entire world to this day. The yin
and yang representing complimentary and
interdependent forces in nature such as
light and dark, hot and cold, or most
notably good and bad. This philosophy
teaches that by balancing these opposing
forces, individuals can achieve harmony
and fulfillment. [music]
Meanwhile, in Meso America, an empire
reached its peak in 900 BC.
Emerging from southern Mexico in 1800
BC, themech spread rapidly, constructing
massive cities with complex sewage
systems,
they gave the western hemisphere its
first writing system, and invented the
concept of the number zero for the first
time in recorded history. Themes are
best known for their colossal heads.
Standing more than 3 meters tall and
weighing over 50 tons, each of these
massive heads is unique. Each is carved
from a single block of volcanic basalt,
which had to be dragged across Mexico
for months on end by teams as large as
1,500 people. Immensemech efforts are
epitomized in the Great Pyramid of
Leventa, where over a thousand tons of
decorative stone are offered in
sacrifice. In the 4th century BC, they
simply vanished from the historical
record, remaining a mystery to this day.
The Mediterranean world had become ever
more globalized. By 800 B.CE, there were
trade routes all the way from Syria to
Spain. At the heart of this vast
network, the Phoenetians,
perhaps the most advanced merchant
civilization in human history, the
Phoenician citystates pioneered mass
production of goods. For their trade,
they became master ship builders,
revolutionizing the cargo ship. Such a
ship could carry up to 250 tons of
cargo. This is because they were the
first to invent the keel, a long wooden
beam running along the bottom of the
ship. Its genius engineering allowed
sailors to navigate rough seas with
greater stability and control. And their
greatest achievement, they transformed
writing forever by creating history's
first practical alphabet, [music]
a simple system of just 22 symbols.
Human writing no longer consisted of
only complicated hieroglyphs. It was
this Phoenician alphabet that over
thousands of years gradually transformed
into the writing systems we use today.
Surprisingly, the Phoenetians did not
build extravagant palaces and instead
reinvested their maritime profits into
setting up trading posts and colonies
throughout the Mediterranean. One
Phoenician colony would go on to form a
massive empire of their own, Carthage.
According
to legend, Carthage was founded by the
Phoenician princess Daido. When she
discovered that her brother, the
tyrannical king Pigon, had murdered her
husband, Daido founded a new home for
herself. In 8:14 CE, Carthage was born.
Under the temperate leadership of its
founding queen, the new city prospered.
Its legendary circular harbor, a
technological wonder, held its
everexpanding [music]
navy, which dominated all others in the
Mediterranean Sea. While the other
Phoenician citystates dwindled in
influence throughout the first
millennium B.C., Carthage expanded. Soon
they had seized territory in Spain,
Sicily, and along the entire North
African coast. Carthage had developed an
identity entirely its own, the capital
of the Punic Empire, dominant power of
the Mediterranean world.
Shortly after founding the city, Queen
Daido fell in love with the wandering
Trojan hero Inas. The two were to be
married when at the last minute, Inas
received a message from Jupiter that he
must depart in secret, and the man sadly
obeyed. Daido, heartbroken, cast herself
on a funeral p, setting fire to herself
in rageful disgrace.
As the queen went up in flames, she used
her last breath to curse Inas, who
sailed west towards his destiny. He
finally landed on the Italian peninsula.
Here, his descendants will go on to
found a new kingdom. Their names were
Romulus and Remis.
In 753 BC, ground was broken on a city
that would soon be the center of [music]
the world. Its founders, the brothers
Romulus and Reheis.
It is said [music] that the two were
abandoned at birth, left to float down
the Tyber River.
Death would no doubt have taken the
infants had a shewolf not rescued and
nursed them back to health, keeping them
alive long enough to be discovered by a
nearby shepherd who took the boys in as
his own. When the boys came of age, they
decided to found a new city here on the
banks of the Tyber River. But the new
city could only have one ruler. [music]
Once the two boys finished building the
city wall, Romulus slew his brother in
cold [music] blood. Rome had its first
king.
Romulus founded a line of seven
legendary kings, each more ruthless than
the last. The Roman kings would see
their city become the most powerful on
the Italian peninsula, conquering its
neighbors in lightning succession. The
birth of Rome marks the end of the Iron
Age, the beginning of a new period known
as classical antiquity.
It will see the western world
transformed.
Reason will take the place of
superstition.
Law will replace anarchy. For now, Rome
is a minor player in the story to
Mediterranean world. In time, it will
change everything
in ancient Mesopotamia. Standing on the
banks of the Tigress River, a weward
young nobleman suddenly had a
revelation. In a flash, the truth was
revealed and he understood the nature of
the entire universe in a way that
contradicted all established religion.
Before Jesus or Muhammad, a new prophet
was born, Zoroast.
Zoroastrianism states that life is a
constant battle between good and evil.
Each individual has complete free will
and must commit to live their life
according to good by following the
tenants of Zoroastrianism.
Such a life can be achieved.
Zoroasters's text spread like wildfire.
Within a century, it was the dominant
religion in Mesopotamia.
Fire temples where the chief deity Ahura
Mazda was worshiped became commonplace
even in small towns. Practices such as
the use of flames were so sacred that
even today in modern-day Iran stands the
Zoroastrian fire temple of Yaz, which
holds a flame which has been burning
since [music] 470 AD.
Zoroastaster would go on to educate
legendary Greek thinkers like Pythagoras
and is regarded by many as the world's
first ethics philosopher. From the
religious to the secular, Zoroaster
remains one of the most influential
thinkers in all of human history.
[music]
From 1,00 to 700 BC, the Assyrian people
conquered the entire Near East. At its
height, their massive empire stretched
from the Mediterranean to the Persian
Gulf. From Anatolia down to the Egyptian
border, ruled from the ancient capital
of Nineveh. Nineveh would become a city
of ancient knowledge with one of the
first libraries in the world to preserve
the literature, science, and stories of
an entire civilization.
Over 30,000 clay tablets from their
library have been recovered and
translated, giving us [music] a detailed
insight into the world of ancient
Mesopotamia.
It turns out women were given near equal
status with men. They could own
property, run businesses, and appear in
legal documents, and racial
discrimination was almost entirely
absent, an extremely rare notion at the
time.
Their culture did not have clear
definitions of race or ethnicity.
Foreigners in Assyrian art have the same
physical features as Assyrians and are
distinguished only by their clothing. By
689 BC, they had displaced the Kushites
and expanded into Egypt. By this point,
however, the Assyrian Empire was
bloated, overextended. Their policy of
rule by terror created mass discontent.
As soon as they went to put down one
revolt, another would emerge. By 600 BC,
the empire had collapsed and [music] the
power that once dominated the Near East
was erased.
[music]
A legendary civilization was just taking
its first steps in Greece. Three
dominant city states emerged from its
centuries long dark age.
First, there was thieves, the cultural
hub of Greece. Home to such mythological
figures as Hercules, Edipus [music] Rex,
and the legendary Sphinx. It was a
beacon of the arts. Then, Athens, the
birthplace of Western civilization.
Legendary philosophers like Socrates,
Plato, and Aristotle produced works that
[music] would shape society for
millennia. and finally Sparta, a fierce
military dictatorship.
At age seven, Spartan boys were taken
from their mothers and became soldiers.
Their training was brutal and were
considered by the ancient world as the
epitome of military discipline,
strength, and fearlessness.
The Greek philosopher Plutarch even
wrote that newborns were presented to a
council of elders for inspection. The
babies who were strong and fit survived
while babies who were weak were left
outside to die. The Greek city states
were fundamentally different yet always
maintained strong cultural ties. Each
year they came together at the panh
helenic games in Olympia. A tradition
maintained to this day now known as the
Olympics.
However, the rivalry between Athens and
Sparta ran deep. The two societies were
simply opposites.
Sparta purposely neglected the arts.
They were unthinking warriors. If a
Spartan child was caught stealing food,
he would be beaten severely, not for the
act of stealing, but for being careless
enough to get caught.
In Athens, the arts and a refined
education were crucial. The Athenians
tried something new and gave mankind the
most important political system in its
history.
[music]
It was the revolutionary statesman
Kleines that brought democracy to Athens
and eventually the world.
In 510 BC, by rallying the full might of
the Athenian middle class, Kleanes
overthrew the tyrant Hippius in a
violent upheaval. In the chaos, the king
of Sparta sent an army to seize control
of a weakened Athens. But Klein and his
populist forces valiantly held them off.
They would determine their own fate.
Solidifying power, Kleanes immediately
decreed that all Athenian citizens would
enjoy equal rights and an equal vote.
His reforms were just getting started.
At the Athenian Assembly, thousands of
citizens gathered at least once a month
to pass new laws. Any citizen could
speak before the assembly, and voting
was done by simple hand raising. One of
the strangest and most effective aspects
of Athenian democracy was the practice
of ostracism. If 6,000 citizens voted
for it, any Athenian citizen could be
exiled for 10 years just like that. 15
known ostracisms would take place over
the next century. In a bitter irony, the
first victim of Klein system of
ostracism was Kleines himself. The
people made full use of the democracy
they'd been given and exiled the
powerful revolutionary.
With the violent death of the Assyrian
Empire, all of Mesopotamia was suddenly
up for grabs. Rising up to fill the
power vacuum, a state that had laid
dormant for a thousand years had
reemerged.
Babylon.
Casting off the Assyrian yoke in 612 BC,
the Babylonians quickly conquered
Mesopotamia from the Persian Gulf to the
Mediterranean. Within the walls of their
magnificent Ishtar Gate, Babylon became
the scientific capital of the ancient
world. It was the Babylonians who
perfected the base 60 number system, and
its legacy is still with us today. 60
seconds in a minute, 60 minutes in an
hour, and 360° in a circle. The
Neoablonian Empire had become the
dominant force in all the Near East.
To commemorate the Renaissance of their
2,000-year-old culture, the Babylonians
built monumental structures of unrivaled
beauty. The legendary Hanging Gardens of
Babylon, a wonder of the ancient world.
This massive tiered complex, 400 ft on
each side, housed rare plant and animal
species from the furthest reaches of the
known world, astonishing outsiders.
While the garden no longer exists today,
parts of the ancient city of Babylon
were reconstructed during the 1980s and
'90s, giving us a glimpse into what the
Neoablonian Empire once was. In 550 BC,
it was the most powerful empire on
earth.
[music]
Sidartha, a spoiled young prince, spent
his entire youth in isolated luxury.
Within the walls of his family's palace,
he [music] could have anything he ever
desired.
Gold, jewels, all of life's material
pleasures.
One day when Sedartha was 29 years old,
he decided to leave the palace. The
first thing he saw was an old man dying
miserably on the side of the road. Try
as he might, Sidarththa could not help
the old man. Sidartha realized in a
flash the horrors of life from which he
had always been sheltered. Life was not
luxury. It was suffering and death. The
young prince immediately left behind his
palace, his family, and his wealth, and
never [music] looked back. He couldn't
save the old man, but perhaps he could
save the rest of humanity. Sidartha made
it his life's purpose to find an escape
[music] from the horrible suffering that
is life. For 6 years, he roamed the land
trying various religious practices, but
nothing satisfied him. One day, he
decided to abandon all these established
practices. He simply sat himself down
beneath a fig tree and [music]
meditated. It soon came to him the
solution to human suffering,
enlightenment. [music]
From that moment on, Sidartha became
known as the enlightened one, the
Buddha. He traveled around India
preaching the path to enlightenment.
Buddhism, a lifelong process of
cultivating inner peace. Beyond the ego,
beyond life and death, lies Buddhist
enlightenment. Nirvana, the end of all
suffering. The maintenance spread would
encourage positive and honest relations
with human beings and the world around
them. Karma would be a fundamental
concept. The Buddha spent the rest of
his life traveling and spreading his
teachings, fulfilling his life's
purpose. To this day, Buddhism is one of
the world's largest religions with over
500 million practitioners globally,
making it the fourth largest religion
after Christianity, Islam, and Hinduism.
In Carthage, one of humanity's first
great explorers was making his mark in
the fifth century BC. Hano the
Navigator, an ambitious young
aristocrat, launched an expedition to
test the limits of the known world.
Embarking beyond the pillars of Hercules
to the infinite outer sea, he and his
intrepid crew traveled 3,000 m in the
rugged Atlantic. Turning south, they
charted the massive west coast of
Africa, reaching all the way down to
Gabone.
Along the way, Hano encountered dozens
of indigenous peoples, some friendly,
some violent. Not to be outdone, the
Greeks launched an expedition of their
own in 325 BC. It would put all others
to shame. Led by the famed explorer
Pytheus of Misalia, the crew quickly
reached the rugged wilds of Northern
Europe, they comprehensively mapped the
British Isles and encountered the
fearsome indigenous Brits, giving
history its first account of their
strange culture. The first ever written
reference to Scotland comes from
Pytheus's travel log. Concluding his
study of the Isisles, Pytheus did not
return home, nor did he travel east.
Against all logic, he headed north into
the vast, frigid North Atlantic.
Traveling hundreds of miles beyond all
signs of land, Pytheus reached the place
where the sun goes to rest, the Arctic
Circle. Here he encountered a frozen
ocean shrouded in fog, where the sun
never set. Land, sea, and air blended
into a strange miasma, what Pytheus
called the marine lung. Completely
unnavigable by ship, sled or foot, the
man had discovered the ultimate limit of
the world.
Meanwhile, in ancient Iran, one of
history's greatest conquerors was born
around 600 BC. Cyrus [music] the Great.
At Cyrus's birth, the local king
received a prophecy. The child would one
day unleash a great flood upon his
empire and seize all that was once his.
The emperor immediately ordered the
infant Cyrus to be killed. But a
shepherd took pity on the boy and raised
Cyrus as his own. When Cyrus's birth
father died, the truth was revealed.
Cyrus was the rightful heir to the
kingdom. But fearing the prophecy from
Cyrus's birth, the local king ordered
him to step down. Cyrus refused to
kneel.
Rallying the forces of his small
kingdom, he staged a daring revolt in
553 BC. To the shock of the ancient
world, he succeeded.
Like that, Cyrus seized an entire
empire. He was just getting started.
First, he conquered the west, reaching
all the way to Greece. Then, he turned
east, expanding his empire to the
frontiers of India. In 539 BC, he set
his sights on Babylon. Within a year,
the entire Neoablonian Empire was his.
In 15 years, Cyrus had gone from the
prince of a subservient kingdom to the
ruler of the largest empire in human
history. He was not just a ruler of the
Mes or the Babylonians. He had created a
new entity, the Persian Empire. Cyrus
was not a ruthless conqueror. He was a
compassionate leader. He provided all of
his foes a peaceful diplomatic option
before resorting to force. Even by those
he conquered, he was remembered as the
father. He created the Cyrus cylinder in
539 BC, [music] which is widely regarded
as the world's first charter of human
rights. These written laws ensured
conquered peoples would keep their
religions and customs instead of forcing
Persian culture and allowed displaced
[music] peoples to return to their
homelands after war.
Just 10 years later, it is said that
Cyrus was killed in battle by a savage
tribe led by Tomerus, [music] a Cythian
queen. The great emperor's monument is a
humble limestone tomb holding his
remains. 2,500 years later, it is still
standing in modern-day Iran.
After Cyrus's death, the Persian Empire
would live on. The new leaders pursued a
course of vigorous expansion. By 515 BC,
under a man named Darius I, the Persian
Empire now included Libya, Egypt, and
much of India. To commemorate the
empire's great heights, a new city was
built, the heart of Persian royal power,
Pepilolis.
Created to house a series of grand
palaces and monumental works. Over 33
acres of land were leveled to create
Pepilolis,
the ultimate symbol of imperial
prestige. Its walls are covered with
inscriptions of guests bringing tribute
from all over the world. and perhaps
their greatest achievement, the
immortals, the empire's most elite
soldiers. Exactly 10,000 men. Whenever
one died, another immediately replaced
him. They used scale armor instead of
using heavier bronze armor. They wanted
to be light on their feet in battle.
With this flexibility, their army had
some of the greatest archers and
horsemen soldiers the world had ever
seen.
In the later years of Darius's reign, he
turned his attention to the western
frontier. Two stubborn little citystates
refused to bend the knee and submit to
his rule. The city states in question,
Athens and Sparta.
Now came the most famous conflict in
history, Persia versus Greece.
When Darius the Great sent ambassadors
to Athens and Sparta demanding
submission, the response left nothing up
to interpretation. The messengers were
immediately put to death.
The very next year in 490 BC, the
massive Persian fleet arrived, carrying
over 100,000 troops, enough to level all
of Greece. They landed at the city of
Marathon, 42 km from Athens. To their
surprise, the Athenian army of 10,000
men met them in Marathon, meaning Athens
was left completely unguarded. The
Persians loaded back onto their ships to
head straight for the empty city of
Athens. But the Athenians did the
unthinkable. Outnumbered 10 to1, they
attacked in Marathon instead. The
Persians were caught completely
offguard. They lost 6,200 troops while
Athens only lost 192. More importantly,
the Battle of Marathon proved that the
Persians could be beaten. The remaining
Persian forces made it to their ships
and departed [music] for Athens. In a
feat of legendary endurance, one Greek
messenger sprinted 40 km from Marathon
to Athens without stopping, racing the
Persian fleet. He burst into the
Athenian assembly, exclaimed, "We have
won." Then died on the spot. The run
later gave birth to the Olympic
marathon, being 42 km in distance, the
exact distance the Athenian army had to
march back home.
The Athenian army made it to Athens in
time, and when the Persians arrived,
they were turned away. Morale and
tatters, they retreated, but the war was
far from over.
In 480 BC, the Persians returned,
determined to reduce Greece to rubble.
At the narrow pass of Thermopoly, they
were confronted by the Spartan king
Leonitis I and his elite personal
bodyguards.
The Persian forces numbered 300,000.
The Spartans only 300. In history's most
legendary last stand, the Spartans
defended their home against the Persian
onslaught for two full days, killing
20,000 Persian troops. Fighting to the
very last man, the Spartans were finally
overrun. Having bought enough time for
Athens to be evacuated, the Persians
proceeded to destroy the abandoned city
of Athens [music] and then chase the
Athenian army to Solomus by sea. But
this was just as the Greeks had planned.
In one of history's most daring
ambushes, the Athenian ships lay waiting
in the Battle of Solomus, launching a
naval attack despite being massively
outnumbered.
The Persian fleet was decimated. Their
troops were now trapped, unable to
retreat and regroup. At the Battle of
Platia, the Greeks delivered the killing
blow, decimating the hopeless Persian
forces. The Greeks lost 5,000 men and
killed over 50,000.
The Persian army entirely crushed,
scattered to the wind. The message was
clear. Fighting to defend their home
soil, the Greeks would never be
conquered. A third invasion never came.
Meso
America was taking a similar path, one
of blood.
In 500 BC, the Zapotch people rose to
power in Mexico. Quickly, they developed
a unique artistic theme which set them
apart from any of their predecessors.
The Zapotch were obsessed with [music]
death. At the top of society were divine
kings who projected their power by
immortalizing tortured and slain enemies
into stone. One set of Zapotch carvings
depicts hundreds of enemy chiefs being
tortured and killed in painful warped
postures. Outside of the arts, the
Zapetch brought another bloody cultural
touchstone to Meso America, human
sacrifice. Human sacrifice was more than
punishment. It became a sacred ritual
used to honor their gods. And so it
never stopped. This innovation would go
on to define later cultures like the
Aztecs and the Mayans.
The Zapotch dominated Mexico for more
than 1,000 years.
When Zapotch civilization crashed, it
did so without a trace. One day, their
urban centers were thriving and the next
they were abandoned. The cause is still
not known.
In 509 BC, the line of seven legendary
kings came to an end in Rome. Instead of
a king, the republic was headed by the
all powerful Senate with two leaders in
charge. The republic's identity was
anti- king, anti-dictator.
For the Romans, nothing was as important
to a man than [music] his reputation as
a soldier. Every military victory made
Rome stronger, and every defeat taught
it how to win the next war. They were
exceptional conquerors for their time.
By the end of the 3rd century BC, they
had conquered all of central Italy. But
in 280 BC, the Greeks landed on the
Italian peninsula.
The Greek general Pius was determined to
defend the Greek cities of Magnagcia.
He brought a level of force the Romans
had never seen.
Massive contingents of hardened Greek
hoplights and more shockingly war
elephants. The Romans were defeated
outright in back-to-back battles. But
Purus suffered heavy losses and had to
retreat. He famously stated, "Another
such victory and I am undone." giving
rise to the term pirick victory. For the
next 2300 years, this saying would be
used to describe a win that came at such
high costs, it feels more like a loss.
Soon, the Romans adapted to this new
challenge, developing techniques to deal
with the rampaging war elephants. When
Purus returned in 275 BC, he was stopped
in his tracks at the Battle of
Benavvenum.
He left and never returned.
The Romans had repelled one of the
Mediterranean world's greatest military
powers. They were unchallenged on the
Italian peninsula and began to look
beyond. The world's most powerful empire
was beginning to take form. But in the
next few hundred years, it would have to
overcome its greatest challenge yet,
their opposing superpower of the ancient
world, Carthage.
Meanwhile, in Asia, the spring and
autumn period of Chinese history between
770 and 481 BC saw some of mankind's
greatest philosophers come to the four.
Feudalism dominated the empire with the
emperor reaping all the benefits of the
peasants hard labor. The people
desperately needed guidance and
philosophers emerged to fill that gap.
Soon a war of ideas was raging.
The three competing philosophies of
Confucianism, Taoism and legalism came
to define an age.
It began with Confucious, an
impoverished commoner from the
countryside. He created a philosophy
centered on hard work and discipline.
According to Confucianism, the important
thing in life is to be loyal to your
family, community, and king. It gave the
surfs of China a sense of purpose, a
reason to work the soil day in and day
out without seeing any reward.
Next came Taoism, the way of the
universe, a counter movement to
Confucianism. [music] Its founder,
Laauu, a reclusive man who withdrew from
civilization to live a simple life in
the mountains. Towoism teaches that we
should question everything in life,
family, government, and most importantly
work. His way of the universe is to live
spontaneously, never forcing anything.
After all, why should we toil away all
our lives making ourselves miserable
while others profit? Among China's
repressed peasant class, the idea spread
like wildfire. The legitimacy of
kingship was completely eroded and
Taloism's principle of the power of the
weak became a rallying cry. Soon the
Zhao dynasty's authority over the empire
was crumbling. The Zhao tribal leaders
all across the kingdom refused to
recognize a universal philosophy and
raised their flags in open rebellion in
480 BC.
By 475 BC, the authority of the Zhao
dynasty had crumbled entirely and
independent states throughout the land
fought bitterly for dominance. By 400
BC, just seven states remained,
deadlocked, unable to conquer each
other. The Han in central China, hailing
from the mountains, these fearsome
tribal warriors were hardened by their
barren, unforgiving environment. The Chu
in the south. The Chu army was the
largest of the seven, but was also
bloated and corrupt, its soldiers soft.
The Chin in the west, isolated from the
rest of the tribes by geographical
barriers, the Chin were radical
innovators. The political mastermind
Shongyang created a new political
philosophy in the Chin state, legalism.
The philosophy of legalism under the
Chin would prove the most effective of
the three. Under legalism, all power was
in the hands of theQin ruler with strict
laws and harsh punishments for the
civilians. All adult males were drafted
into military service. The entire force
of the state would be directed toward
making [music] war. And soon they began
seeing results. In 300 BC, a massive
annexation of Chu territory. In 255 BC,
the Han are subjugated. By 225 BC,
theQin are an unstoppable force. The
remaining states form a defensive
alliance, but it is too late. By 221 BC,
all of China has fallen to the Chin war
machine. Chin Xi Huang was crowned the
first emperor of China.
Fresh from the chaos of a bloody civil
war, China's first emperor went to
extreme lengths to protect his rule.
Feudalism was abolished. The map of the
kingdom completely redrawn and massive
defenses built to prevent foreign
conquest.
The Great Wall of China,
one of the seven wonders of the world,
its construction would continue for the
next 2,000 years. Countless dynasties
left their mark through battles fought
and extending the Great Wall. To this
day, it stretches 21,000 km, and if laid
end to end, it would wrap around Earth
more than halfway.
Emperor Chin constructed the legendary
Terracotta Army. Thousands of clay
soldiers, a symbol of his unrivaled
power.
Each of the soldiers have unique facial
features which suggest that the artisans
who created the army modeled the faces
after real people. For the mad tyrant
though, none of this was enough. In 230
BC, an assassination attempt nearly
seized his life. While Chin was on the
road, a massive boulder was pushed from
a cliff overhead. It crashed into the
cart directly in front of the emperor.
What good was a secure rule if
everything could be stripped away by a
lone assassin? Chin began to search for
a permanent solution, immortality.
His court alchemists were dispatched
throughout the land, searching for the
elixir of life. Hundreds of failed
experiments ensue. Men claiming to have
discovered the elixir were buried alive,
a test of their immortality.
In 211 BC, a massive meteor crashed into
the Yellow River. To Chin, it was a
sign. The boulder that had so nearly
crushed him all those years ago would
strike again. His death [music] was
imminent. The emperor went into a panic
and began testing hundreds of elixirs on
himself, desperately fighting the
looming spectre of death. One year
later, Emperor Chinshi Huang was dead.
The cause, ingestion of mercury, a
failed elixir.
In his quest for an elixir of life, the
emperor found only cold mortality.
The prophecy of his death fulfilled
itself.
[music]
In Arabia, a group of tribal nomads were
building a civilization of immense
wealth and complexity in the vast desert
plains. By 300 BC, the shepherds had
built a trade network in the Middle East
of unrivaled wealth, covering the rich,
untamed Arabian Peninsula. Using a
series of fables and myths to encode
their secret trade routes, they
navigated the region in a way outsiders
could never understand. Their vast
wealth was eyed greedily by the
Persians, the Greeks, and the expanding
Romans. But the Nabatans nevertheless
resisted domination by these powerful
militaries for centuries. [music] The
Nabatans were not only clever merchants,
they also constructed some of the most
beautiful architecture known to man.
Their ancient capital of Petra, also
known as the Rose City, is one of the
seven wonders of the world.
Advanced technological features were
incorporated into their stand buildings
such as dams, sistns, and water
conduits. They have become known as the
most unjustly forgotten people in
mankind's history.
For centuries, the great and historic
citystates of Athens and Sparta [music]
dominated Greece. People like the
Macedonians, fierce cavalry men secluded
in the Greek mountains, were nothing
more than an afterthought. In the 4th
century BC, however, Philip II, King of
Macedonia, led his mountain warriors in
a charge of fearless ambition. In 359
BC, he defeated the Athenians and
stunned the Greek world.
Philip then conquered Thrace and sent a
warning to the Spartans.
Philip rallied his forces, but before he
could act, disaster struck. At his
daughter's wedding, one of his own
bodyguards turned on the great king and
stabbed him to death as the wedding
guests watched helplessly. Like that,
the man who had built Macedonia into a
major Greek power, was dead. Power fell
to his son, only 20 years old. The
Macedonian people mourned. The death of
their kingdom was in sight. Yet,
Philip's son was no ordinary
20-year-old. He had been educated by the
legendary philosopher Aristotle and was
believed by some to be the child of Zeus
himself.
Alexander of Macedonia.
Before King Philip of Macedonia was
killed, he said to his son, "You must
find a kingdom big enough for your
ambitions. Macedonia is too small for
you." Alexander did just that. Quickly
conquering the Balkans and raising
thieves to the ground in 335 BC, he set
his focus on the Persian Empire. The
young general made it look easy.
By 333 BC, he had taken all of Asia
Minor from the bloated Aanits and was
pressing into the Middle East. Here he
was presented with the mythical Gordian
knot, which could only be untied by the
future king of Asia. In characteristic
fashion, Alexander hacked it to pieces
with a sword and continued his march. In
333 BC at Isis, he dealt Darius III such
a crushing defeat that the entire
Persian army nearly collapsed. Darius
offered Alexander an incredibly generous
peace deal, seeding all the territory he
now occupied, plus a massive tribute.
Alexander brushed Darius aside, replying
that since he was now king of Asia, he
would decide how territory should be
divided. By 332 BC, he had taken Egypt,
where they welcomed him as a liberator.
In 331 BC, he once more crushed Darius's
forces.
Darius was captured and put to death.
The entire Persian Empire belonged to
Alexander [music] of Macedonia.
Looking yet further east, he marched his
Greek forces into India, where they
encountered fierce tribes that made use
of war elephants.
At the Beas River, having endured years
of brutal campaigning, Alexander's
troops refused to go an inch further.
They returned home to manage the
mind-boggling swath of territory they
had conquered. In 5 years, Alexander had
gone from the head of a minor Greek
polity to the king of the known world,
an empire 2 million square miles in
size.
>> [music]
>> Alexander died in the palace of
Nebuchadnezzar II in Babylon. His sudden
death would come from a fever in 3:23
BC. He was only 32 years old.
Speculations would arise surrounding his
death. Tales of poisoning emerged with a
list of alleged perpetrators, including
one of Alexander's wives, his generals,
his illegitimate half-brother, or the
royal cupbearer. On his deathbed, he was
asked, "Who shall have the empire?" He
replied, "To the strongest."
The gigantic Macedonian Empire was
divided among his top generals. Tommy I
ruled in Egypt, establishing a long line
of learned scholarly pharaohs. The new
capital of Alexandria became the world's
main hub of philosophy, science, and
technology. In Macedonia, the Antiggoned
dynasty struggled to retain control of
restless Greek citystates. By 200 BC,
they were colliding with an expanding
Roman Republic and began to crumble. In
the east, the general Salucas was left
with a vast Seucid Empire, greatest of
all the successor states.
One of the most diverse domains in
history, the Seucids were Greeks,
Persians, and many more. These disperate
groups had been united under Alexander's
magnetic influence. With his death, the
empire quickly began to decline.
It was India that struck first against
the bloated Seucid Empire. Shandra Gupta
Moria, a young peasant from the Indian
countryside, had witnessed Alexander's
invasion firsthand as a young man. In
the wake of the great conqueror's death,
a series of tyrannical Greek
administrators were installed to rule
India. Imitating the great Alexander,
Moria assembled a makeshift army of
mercenaries, hunters, and bandits and
stormed the Greek administrative center.
In 317 BC, his forces managed to seize
the Greek governors and put them to the
blade. The Indian people flocked to
Morius banner. He began seizing
neighboring provinces and soon had
driven the Greeks all the way past the
Indis River. Like Alexander, Morian had
founded a vast new polity, the Morian
Empire. All that remained was to conquer
the rest of tribal India. A job left for
Morian's son, one of the country's most
successful and beloved rulers to this
day, Ashoka the Great.
In 260 BC, Ashoka launched a brutal war
against the Kolinga peoples in Eastern
India.
100,000 were killed and another 150,000
taken prisoner. It was a turning point
in the young emperor's life. Witnessing
such unthinkable bloodshed caused
entirely by himself forever changed
Ashoka. In a moment of divine
revelation, he renounced violence and
became a devout Buddhist, refusing to
harm even animals. The transformed
emperor ruled India in peace and
prosperity for another 40 years. The
slave trade was abolished. Massive
public works constructed and Buddhism
flourished in the kingdom.
Ashoka brought India into a golden age.
On a small island in the Pacific Ocean,
another complex, unique civilization was
taking its first [music] steps. For
thousands of years, a tribal lifestyle
of fishing, farming, and crafting
flourished in Japan.
However, in the fifth century BC, the
powerful Joe dynasty in China took an
interest in the little island.
The Chinese brought bronze weapons and
armor, a powerful aristocracy, and the
development of urban centers. Their
biggest impact would be the introduction
of rice farming to Japan. Rice would
dominate the island. The more rice one
could make, the more powerful they would
become. And so, kings began to emerge.
Japanese kingdoms were born.
Just like India, Egypt was also
revolutionized in the wake of
Alexander's rapid ascent and death. His
Greek general, Tommy I, reigning in the
new capital of Alexandria, turned Egypt
into the world's premier hub of
learning. The legendary library of
Alexandria was constructed, harboring
400,000 scrolls. It housed all the
knowledge of the ancient world and
attracted academics from all reaches.
The famed Greek mathematician Archimedes
lived in the library. He discovered the
principle of buoyancy, designing the
formula for keeping anything afloat on
water. He was the inventor of the
Archimedes screw, a device that uses a
helical screw inside a cylinder to lift
water from a lower level to a higher
one. Eratosineses
also lived in the library. He managed to
calculate the earth's circumference with
a staggering 99% accuracy in 190 BC. The
city also housed the world's first
man-made harbor [music] where another
technological marvel stood. The Ferros,
the lighthouse of Alexandria. A wonder
of the ancient world and for centuries
the tallest man-made structure. This
massive flaming beacon stunned visitors.
Under its watchful gaze, Alexandria
quickly became a bustling merchant port.
By 200 BC, it was the largest city in
the world. For centuries, the Tamies
thrived in Egypt. Eventually, though,
forces of the unstoppable Roman Republic
will reach its borders, and the Tamies
will be powerless to resist.
A rainforest so large it spans across
[music] nine different countries.
The Amazon.
Beneath the trees is a world of its own.
Home to over 10 million species.
Even to this day, humans cannot tame the
land. It's a place so wild, so
relentless that the natural order
remains perfectly [music] intact.
Survival is the law, and every living
being must fight for its place. The
humans that were born in this chaotic
paradise were like no other. The
unforgiving nature would force the
humans to adapt. They had larger feet,
helping them navigate through the
terrain of the rainforest. They had
enhanced vision, especially in low light
conditions. This improved awareness was
crucial for hunting and navigating the
forest at dawn or dusk. The earliest
Amazonian peoples resided in the valley
in Ecuador beginning in 500 BC. Here
they constructed houses on massive
platforms elevating them from the jungle
floor. These raised platforms could be
as large as 60,000 square ft holding
countless homes among the lush
vegetation.
Amazonian cities. Collections of these
platform neighborhoods housed as many as
100,000 people at their peak. European
explorers found countless wonders in the
Amazon. One such city was said to be
ruled by a king so wealthy that each
morning he would cover himself from head
to toe in gold dust. The city was named
after its legendary king, the golden
one, El Dorado.
Back on the Italian peninsula, the
Romans still reign supreme. In 264 BC,
however, they faced the full might of a
global superpower for the first time,
Carthage. The Carthaginians had long
held territory in Sicily, which was
becoming intolerable to the expanding
Romans. The first Punic War was long and
contentious,
but eventually ended in a decisive Roman
victory. Fighting in their homeland,
Carthage withdrew, directing its efforts
at colonizing Spain. It wasn't long
before the two states were at each
other's throats again. In 218 BC, the
Romans ignited the second Punic War. Led
by Hannibal, one of history's greatest
military tacticians, the Carthaginians
crossed the Alps with North African war
elephants and invaded the Italian
peninsula. At the Battle of Lake
Trazamine and the Battle of Canai, he
dealt Rome two of its most crushing
defeats of all time. The Carthaginians
lost about 10,000 men. The Romans
100,000.
Just when Rome was within his reach,
Hannibal did the unthinkable. He
retreated, returning to Carthage to
defend from a Roman counterattack. In an
instant, he threw away a clear chance at
victory. It is perhaps the greatest
strategic mistake in history.
The Romans quickly seized the momentum,
prepared a massive invasion force, and
defeated Hannibal in Carthage in 202 BC.
>> [music]
>> The Carthaginians were stripped of all
overseas territories and reduced to
nothing more than a tiny kingdom in
North Africa. In 149 BC, the Romans
finished the job. They launched the
third Punic War for no other reason than
to wipe Carthage off the map. As the
Roman ships came into sight, there could
have been no doubt that the time had
come. The Romans tore down the walls and
conducted a slaughter of unforeseen
brutality.
750,000
Carthaginian citizens were killed,
50,000 enslaved. When the city had
burned, the Romans famously salted the
earth, ensuring crops would never again
grow on Carthaginian soil. Carthage was
no more. Rome controlled Italy, Greece,
and much of Spain, though they were far
from satisfied.
Back in Europe, the Roman legions
continued to conquer. In 86 BC, they
reached Athens. For centuries, Athens
had been the cultural center of the
ancient world. Now, it was just another
Roman client state.
The Roman general Pompi would campaign
to lands never before seen by the
Romans. Pompi would reach Judea in 63 BC
and it was him who brought Roman
dominance to the region. Having just
conquered the kingdom of Pontis and what
remained of the Seucid Empire, Pompi was
quickly becoming known as the conqueror
of Asia. In 63 BC, the kingdom of Judea
was made a Roman province. The kingdom
of Galilee was conquered in the same
year. Within these lands lay the Jewish
people, an ancient civilization whose
belief in a single god set them apart
from almost every other people of their
time. Though now under Roman rule, they
fiercely preserve their identity, laws,
and traditions.
Another Roman general, Julius Caesar,
would conquer in the opposite direction,
battling fierce tribes across modern-day
France, Germany, and Britain. These
tribal peoples were formidable enemies,
skilled, fearless warriors, often
fighting completely naked. After almost
10 years of fighting, Julius Caesar had
emerged [music] victorious, expanding
Rome's borders farther than ever before.
Seeking absolute power, Caesar and his
army then marched on Rome itself,
battling his rival Pompi in a bloody
civil war. Defeated, Pompy's great Roman
territories were no longer his own. Rome
now belonged entirely to Julius Caesar.
The republic with two ruling consils was
no more and the Roman sailed Caesar as
their dictator.
But Rome itself was facing a growing
food crisis. Its grain supplies
dwindling, the people starving. [music]
Julius Caesar would visit Egypt and meet
with the Egyptian pharaoh Cleopatra.
Mesmerized by her charm and
intelligence, the two become lovers.
Their relationship brought together two
of the ancient world's greatest
civilizations. With the grain of Egypt
flowing into the city, Rome's food
crisis was over.
While the people rejoiced, the Senate
were not ready to give up on the
republic, fearing Caesar will cement
dictatorship in Rome. In 44 BC, during a
Senate meeting, the Roman senators rose
from their seat with daggers [music] and
surrounded Caesar. 60 conspirators had
agreed to each stab the dictator once,
all implicating themselves in the murder
and restoration of the Roman Republic.
In the end, Caesar was stabbed just 23
times. To the Senate, the Republic was
saved.
But their efforts were no match for
Octavian, Caesar's adopted son. He
himself would destroy the republic and
even defeat Cleopatra, taking Rome and
Egypt for himself. The last pharaoh of
Egypt was dead and the first emperor of
Rome crowned. Octavian adopted the
imperial name Augustus [music] in 27 BC.
The republic was officially over. The
Roman Empire was born.
Augustus was the first and yet perhaps
the greatest Roman Emperor. Until the
empire's death, [music] its leaders
would adopt the title Augustus in honor
of the man who had started it all.
They would go on to construct the
ultimate monument to the Roman military
spirit, the Colosseum.
The massive amphitheater housed
performances of unimaginable splendor.
The most famous attraction, gladiators.
Slaves, prisoners, and daring Roman
athletes were thrust into combat, either
with each other or fearsome beasts from
across the globe, while bloodthirsty
Roman crowds cheered them on. A golden
age had dawned over the new empire.
[music]
27 years after Augustus was crowned
emperor, a child of unrivaled
significance would be born in the Roman
province of Galilee. At the time,
Augustus had resolved to conduct an
empirewide census. The boy's expectant
parents had to travel all the way to
Bethlehem to register with Roman
officials. The city was so crowded they
were forced to take shelter in a barn.
That night, the mother could wait no
longer. Jesus of Nazareth was born. The
boy, raised a humble carpenter in a
Jewish household, would soon become the
most important philosopher and religious
figure the world has ever known. In 30
AD, the young man traveled to Judea to
preach radical love, tolerance, and
ultimate salvation. He welcomed those
labeled as sinners to his flock,
believing in universal forgiveness. As
the years of Jesus went on, stories
about him grew. More and more followers
began to worship Jesus as their Messiah.
They claimed that he can catch an
endless amount of fish. They claim that
he can cure the blind. and they claimed
that he was the son of God. Disciples
like Matthew, Mark, and Luke committed
their lives to spreading his message.
Soon the young man was being hailed as
the king of the Jews. Although many
admired Jesus, some saw him as a danger.
Those considered a threat to Rome were
often subjected to treason trials, which
commonly led to executions or forced
suicides. Pontius Pilate, the prefect of
Judea at the time, was no stranger to
severe punishments for those found
guilty. The Jewish authorities argued
that anyone claiming to be king of the
Jews posed a threat to the emperor and
Roman rule. However, despite finding no
clear crime deserving death, Pontius
Pilate gave into pressure and ultimately
chose to execute Jesus by crucifixion.
Beaten and humiliated, Jesus walked
towards the moment that would change
history forever. As Jesus was crucified
on the cross, a new religion was born,
Christianity.
On the land we know today as the United
Kingdom, there thrived the Britons,
masterful seafarers and fearsome
warriors. Their society was simple.
Divided into tribes, they farmed,
fished, and made war. By 60 AD, however,
half the island was under Roman control.
They established a Roman city called
Londinium along the river Tempames. The
Britain were losing their home. The time
had come to act.
Buudaca was a Britain warrior queen.
When her father died in 61 AD, the
kingdom she was set to inherit was
annexed by the Romans. The queen was
publicly fgged and her children
tortured. Yet her spirit was unbroken.
Buudaca led a massive revolt against the
Romans, uniting the tribes of the north
against their invaders.
dealing the Romans defeat after defeat,
her barbarian forces sacked Londinium,
putting every Roman settler they could
find to the sword, 80,000 in all.
However, within a year, the Romans had
regrouped, and the legendary Roman
general Swatonius dealt Buudaca a
crushing defeat in the West Midlands.
The queen, seeing that she could not
change the fate of her home, committed
suicide.
Roman control was reasserted throughout
[music] Britain. Londinium was rebuilt
and soon became a bustling metropolis.
Today we know it by a different name,
London. It was the Romans who paved the
roads that still exist within the now
modern city.
In Peru, [music]
some of history's greatest craftsmen
came to power, the Moche.
They rose to prominence in 100 AD and
although they lived in one of the driest
areas in the entire [music] world, a
plane that receives no rainfall
throughout the year, the Mochce were
undeterred.
They were able to build impressive
pyramids like the Wakad del [music] Soul
and Wakadel Luna.
Monumental structures that were the
center of their religions.
Their ceramics depict detailed scenes of
war, religion, daily life, mythology,
and even sexuality.
Countless artifacts depict [music]
intimate and sexual acts, making Mochce
art one of the most openly erotic
[music] bodies of work in South America.
In 600 AD, the Mochce were ravaged by
environmental disasters and their
civilization collapsed. Their ability to
craft a thriving society in one of the
world's harshest environments remains a
testament to human ingenuity.
To the south of the Mochce, a much more
bizarre civilization was developing the
Nazca. The crowning achievement of the
Nazca was their drawings, the Nazca
lines.
For reasons unknown, the Nazca
constructed massive drawings in the
desert soil stretching many miles in
length.
These massive [music] pictures depicting
monkeys, birds, or children can only be
seen fully from the air. The Nazca could
have no way of seeing their own
creations unless they had some means of
flying. The mysterious Nazca line
survive to this day 2,000 years after
their [music] construction.
Mexico would soon witness the peak of
ancient civilization. The city of Teot
Tiwakon, founded in 100 AD, Teayot
Tiwakon boomed to an incredible 250,000
residents by the year 300. The great
city was built in an orderly grid
pattern capped at the north and south
ends by the legendary Pyramid of the
Moon and Pyramid of the Sun. One of the
greatest works of ancient architecture
in the Americas, the Pyramid of the Sun
was built with an incredible 42 million
cubic feet of stone. The streets of
Teayotiwakon are decorated with tens of
thousands of murals, colorful and alive,
unlike any city in history. The
beautifully constructed temples hid away
unthinkable savagery and brutality.
Human sacrifice.
On August 24th, 79 AD, Mount Vuvius
exploded in a violent eruption. The city
of Pompei and everyone within was
consumed entirely.
Pompei's destruction had long been
known, but when modern archaeologists
began to examine the city, they made a
horrifying discovery. The bodies of the
volcano's victims were petrified in ash,
preserved for thousands of years in the
exact positions they held when they
died. Lying, sitting, or praying, Pompei
offers thousands of final moments
captured in an instant.
In Jerusalem, the Jewish people faced
repression, bloodshed, and strife. The
people needed a leader. And in 132 AD,
he arrived. Simon Barokba, a brilliant
tactician, he rallied the people of
Jerusalem to revolt against Roman
oppression. In a violent uprising, they
stormed the administrative center and
put the Roman governor to death.
An independent Jewish state was born
with Barakba as its king. The Roman
Emperor Hadrien outraged sent forces to
put the revolt down, but Barakba
defeated them outright. He then led a
massively successful counterattack and
seized the entire Roman province of
Judea.
Two entire Roman legions were destroyed.
By 133 AD, Parkba's army had swelled to
400,000 strong. Adrien personally rode
to Judea at the head of 10 legions. The
emperor laid siege to the city of Betar.
The city fell and Barakba was killed in
the ensuing skirmish. Without its
prophesized leader, the revolt fell to
pieces. In the aftermath, the Romans
wreaked bloody retribution on the
inhabitants of Judea. Men, women, and
children. None were spared. When the
dust settled, 600,000 Jewish civilians
were dead at the hands of the Romans.
They renamed the region Syria Palestina,
ensuring every trace of the revolt and
the kingdom of Israel was wiped from the
face of history.
Meanwhile, in the land of China, the Han
dynasty was experiencing a renaissance.
After overthrowing the Qin dynasty, they
reigned over a unified China from 202 BC
to 220 AD. They transformed society by
replacing the harsh legalism rule with
Confucianism values of order, ethics,
and learning. This led to some of
China's most remarkable scholarly
achievements in its long history. The
world's first calculator was invented
known as the Chinese abacus. It allowed
equations of staggering complexity to be
solved which led to the invention of
linear algebra. When in the right hands,
square root equations and complex long
divisions were possible. Hon scholars
introduced the world to negative numbers
and discovered the mathematical constant
of pi. This was predicted to eight
decimal places. An accuracy which would
only be matched in Europe 900 years
later. Paper as we know it today was
invented and used by the Han dynasty
also 900 years before being matched in
Europe. By 180 AD, Han scholars had
invented air conditioning, the
belt-driven sewing machine, and the
waterhe. And for the first time ever,
these innovations wouldn't be isolated
to the Chinese world. That's because the
Han then initiated one of the most
ambitious and important economic
endeavors in human history, the Silk
Road.
Stretching from the South China Sea all
the way to Rome, the massive trade
network would connect the ancient world
on a scale never before seen. China, a
land so long shrouded in mystery, was
suddenly accessible. Not just rare and
exotic goods, but ideas and discoveries.
But all good things must come to an end.
In 184 AD, over 2 million peasants all
throughout China rose up in an armed
rebellion against the Han. Whilst they
weren't victorious, they exposed China
and soon regional warlords decided to
strike. The next h 100red years saw a
brutal civil war between many factions.
In 280, the Jyn would conquer all of the
provinces and China [music] was
reunited. A new era began.
Wu, the first Jin Emperor, quickly
became more focused on women than
fulfilling his political duties. In 281,
5,000 women were brought to his palace.
And with all their beautiful women now
at his disposal, Emperor Woo was
overwhelmed with choice and had
difficulty deciding whom he should have
sex with. His famous solutions to this
problem was to ride around in a
goat-drawn cart. Wherever the goat
stopped, Woo would get out and have sex
with whichever woman was there. Some of
the women began leaving bamboo leaves
and salt outside their bedrooms, hoping
to lure the goats into stopping at their
rooms. Woo was utterly sex crazed, using
this goat-drawn method nearly every day
for 8 years. It wasn't long before all
of China had heard of his exploits, and
whispers of rebellion began to spread
like wildfire.
In Rome, hatred for the emperor was just
as strong. From 235 to 284 AD, a series
of dictatorial soldier emperors seized
the throne, bringing the empire to the
brink of collapse. When things looked
most bleak, a hero emerged. Diolesian, a
general himself, Dialesian instituted
sweeping reforms to return stability to
the Roman Empire. Most important, the
tetrarchy. Rome was split into four
quadrants, each ruled by a separate
emperor. Dialesian and gallerius to the
east, Maximian and Constantius Chloris
[music] to the west. For his efforts,
Dialesian was hailed as the founder of
eternal peace.
However, it was not in the nature of a
Roman to share power. Soon, the
co-emperors of the tetrarchy were at
each other's throats, vying for ultimate
control. the greatest of them,
Constantine, who was the son of
Constantius Chloris. A military
mastermind, he [music] outmaneuvered his
rivals at every turn. Soon, all that
stood between Constantine and sole
control of Rome was Maximian's son,
General Maxius.
To try and secure his hold on power,
Maxius ordered the construction of a new
bridge across the Tyber River near Rome,
known as the Milvian Bridge. In 312 AD,
Constantine marched onto the bridge and
the two men faced off, declaring battle,
where Constantine was outnumbered 2 to1.
Yet, the great general felt no fear. The
night before battle, he had a dream of
his men emerging victorious. In this
vision, their shields and standards were
painted with an unexpected symbol, the
Christian cross. Before battle,
Constantine hurriedly had his men
decorate themselves with Christian holy
symbols. The battle was fierce and
brutal with both sides suffering heavy
losses. Maxentius had a larger army, but
his troops were spread out and
disorganized. Constantine was able to
take advantage of this, and he was able
to push Maxentius' forces back [music]
toward the Tyber River. In the chaos of
the retreat, Maxentius was forced off
the Milvian Bridge and into the river
where he drowned. Constantine marched
triumphantly into Rome and declared
himself the sole emperor, crediting his
victory to the Christian God.
Christianity was legalized in Rome and
in the east, a new capital was founded,
Constantinople.
The very empire that crucified Jesus now
embraced his followers with open arms.
Christianity had become the faith of
Rome.
In Africa too, Christianity was coming
to the four. It began in the kingdom of
Axom, a military powerhouse centered in
modern-day Ethiopia. The belligerent
king Azana came to the throne in 330 AD
promising aggressive expansion. When he
took the throne, however, Azana became
entranced with a humble Christian slave
from Lebanon. He granted the slave his
freedom, but the slave refused to leave.
He spoke to the [music] aggressive young
king about Christian principles of love
and forgiveness, and Isana [music]
listened. Entranced, the king converted
to Christianity in 330 AD and abandoned
the path of war. Izzana devoted himself
instead to building great architectural
works in the name of God.
Most impressive of all, the obelisk of
Axom,
a 1700year-old,
24 m tall granite monument carved in a
single [music] piece. Decorated with
hundreds of doors, they represent the
kingdom of heaven and [music] still
stand to this day.
>> [music]
>> In the north, years of drought, climate
disaster, and famine led to the most
massive population shift in human
history in 375 AD, the great migration.
Hundreds of thousands of barbarians
poured into Rome from Gaul and the
Balkans. Rome, already weak from within,
struggled to settle and control the
endless waves of migrants. From the
outside, the Romans would have an even
larger threat, the Visigoths.
In the year 410 AD, the Visigoths would
pull off the most famous sacking in
human history, the sacking of Rome.
For 3 days straight, the storied city
was brutally pillaged. Timeless art and
riches were looted. Civilians killed.
Women captured and enslaved. The days of
Rome were numbered.
The killing blow to Rome came in 476 AD
after the empire refused to grant the
Ostrogoths their desired land in
compensation for defending Rome.
Odoacer, a brilliant Ostrogoth general,
marched his barbarian forces to the
land. He found there a child emperor,
[music] Romulus Augustus, named after
Rome's founder and its first emperor.
Easily defeating the child, Odoacaser
did not proclaim himself the new Roman
Emperor. Instead, he created a new
title, the king of Italy. The Western
Roman Empire was no more. Odoacaser
didn't kill Romulus because he was just
a kid and not seen as a threat. Romulus
was sent into retirement with a pension
at a chapel still standing tall today,
the Castellum Lucalum.
Odoacaser made the city of Ravena his
capital and Rome [music] once the
cultural and economic center of the
world faded into obscurity. Rome defined
an age.
Its fall marked the end of antiquity.
[music]
The dawn of a new age, the Middle Ages.
With the fall of the Roman Empire,
civilizations the world over were left
to determine their own path. Where they
land will determine the fate of the
medieval world. In Europe, barbarian
tribes settled into small kingdoms, each
jockeying for control over the others.
The Visigoths in Spain, the Franks in
France, the Anglo-Saxons in England,
Europe was up for grabs, and any one
power might emerge on top. In the East,
the empire centered in Constantinople
was still one of the world's greatest
powers. Its culture had diverged so
drastically from the Roman Empire of
Antiquity, however, that it was given a
new name, the Byzantine Empire. The
Byzantines faced threats on all sides.
the Persians in the east and the Slavs
in the west. Warfare was constant and as
the Middle Ages begun, they found
themselves on the defensive. The advent
of the wheeled plow boosted food
production and led to a population boom
throughout the medieval [music]
world. Innovations in quilted and
leather armor, meanwhile, meant that the
average foot soldier stood a much better
chance in combat. China was thriving in
all counts, enjoying a renaissance in
the arts [music] and sciences. While the
Cisanian Empire had just reached its
greatest territorial extent, Rome had
been a tremendous empire. But the world
did not end with its demise. The rest of
humanity looked to the future and sought
to carve out its place in the medieval
world.
[music]
In India, a golden age was ushered in by
the Gupta Empire, uniting nearly all of
the subcontinent under their [music]
rule. By 500 AD, Gupta emperors heavily
patronized the arts and sciences. The
canonical texts of Hinduism, including
the [music] epic Mahabarata, were
composed.
Aryabada a Gupta astronomer and
mathematician not only determined that
the earth was in fact a sphere but he
calculated its circumference to be
39,968
km. The actual circumference is 40,75
km.
He would be 99.7%
accurate. He also recognized that
planets shine by reflecting sunlight not
by emitting their own light.
The base 10 numeral system we still use
today was invented and the mathematical
constant pi was calculated.
Architectural wonders were created.
Cut into the mountainside. The agenta
caves were a sanctuary for Buddhism
decorated with beautiful paintings and
sculptures. The Gupta golden age even
brought the first ever game of chess.
While the European kingdoms tore each
other apart in near constant warfare,
India thrived in peace.
In the Eastern Roman Empire, a young man
clawed his way through the ranks from
peasant all the way to emperor Justinian
the Great. When he took the throne in
527 AD, the young man set out to do the
impossible to reunite the Roman Empire
in its entirety.
His success was miraculous.
Dealing the Persians several crushing
defeats to secure the eastern frontier,
he turned to North Africa and quickly
seized it from the barbarian Vandal
Kingdom. His generals moved on from
Spain with equal success, reestablishing
Roman rule on the peninsula. Justinian,
meanwhile, moved into Italy, claiming
Sicily while his generals took the
Balkans and Northern Italy. In 538, he
did the unthinkable, crushing the
Ostrogoths at every turn. Justinian
reclaimed all of Italy, including the
city of Rome.
The empire rejoiced. Justinian had
somehow managed to restore not only
Rome's territorial holdings, but her
pride. The magnificent empire would have
a population of 25 million. To
commemorate his achievements, Justinian
constructed a Christian cathedral in
Constantinople. The Hegia Sophia, one of
humanity's greatest [music]
architectural achievements. Its massive
dome, about 31 m wide, was considered an
engineering marvel and inspired many
future buildings, including Islamic
mosques. Of course, the great emperor
couldn't live forever. After his death
in 565, all he had conquered would
slowly slip away, placed in the hands of
lesser men. As beautiful a moment it may
have been, there was simply no room in
the medieval world for Justinian's
resurgent Roman Empire.
The year 536 saw the most unbelievable
disaster occur.
Three volcanoes erupted spaced all
throughout the world at the exact same
time.
What should have been a local disaster
quickly became a global extinction level
threat. The emissions from these
eruptions were so concentrated that the
sun would not shine for a whole year.
Byzantine historian Precopius wrote,
"The sun gave forth its light without
brightness." In China, there was snow
during summer. Skies darkened and dust
fell like rain. Crops failed and famine
was rampant. But that wasn't all. The
same year, the plague of Justinian broke
out. It would go on to kill 50 million
people, half the world's population. As
though that wasn't enough, Earth entered
what would become known as the Little
Ice Age. Global temperatures dropped
even further and more crops failed in an
unending frost.
And yet, as always, humanity endured.
Blooded, beaten, and half extinct, but
alive.
Buddhism traveled east the same way all
goods moved in the sixth century. The
Silk Road. From India, it reached Korea
where it was embraced by the wise king
of Becka, a master of foreign relations.
When Sun came to Japan in 538 AD with
his message of peace and enlightenment,
he faced violent backlash. Japan was
still a fierce travel society and did
not embrace change. The king tried to
peacefully spread his message, but even
those in favor of Buddhism managed to
find a violent radical interpretation of
its teachings. Relations between
traditionalists and radical Buddhists
quickly deteriorated. When the
traditionalists began defacing the image
of the Buddha in 593 AD, allout war
erupted. The traditionalists however had
lost their base of support amongst the
people and were now nothing more than a
few scattered sects of dissident.
Buddhism had been accepted at the
highest levels of the Japanese
government and the war for Buddhism was
short-lived. A decisive victory for the
Buddhists. Acceptance of Buddhism marks
the dawn of a new era in Japan. The
Asuka period, a golden age for the arts,
architecture, and political reform.
Buddhism had spread across Japan, but
back to the west, a new religion would
be born.
[music]
In the small town of Mecca, a nomadic
tribe called the Kuresh gave birth to a
man who would change the religious
world, Muhammad. Muhammad was orphaned
and brought up first by his grandfather,
then by his uncle. As he matured, he
became a merchant, gaining a reputation
for honesty and earning the title Alamin
or the trustworthy. On one of his
pilgrimages in 610, Muhammad meditated
in a cave on Mount Jabal al-nur. It was
there he received an angelic prophecy
outlining the proper way to live, the
Quran. He was 40 years old at the time,
and he took his teachings to the streets
of Mecca, passionately preaching to
anyone who would listen. His message
spread like wildfire.
The oppressed peoples of Mecca flocked
to his sermons, hailing Muhammad as a
prophet and savior. Islam was born.
However, when Muhammad denounced idol
worship, the leader of Mecca knew that
he was through. In 6:15, he and his
Muslim followers were banished, cast
into the desert. After 7 years of
wandering hopelessly, [music] they were
finally welcomed into the town of
Medina. There, Muhammad was instrumental
in ending various civil wars, creating a
prosperous Muslim community.
Nevertheless, this prosperity would be
challenged by the members of Muhammad's
old tribe, the Qur and their allies, who
marched up to Medina with a large army
to attack the Muslims. Before he knew
it, Muhammad was at war. At the battle
of Batter in 624 AD, his Islamic forces
were outnumbered 3 to1 by the Meccans,
shocking the entire Arab Peninsula.
Muhammad slaughtered the Meccan forces.
Word began to spread that the man really
did have God on his side. Soon, his army
of 300 had expanded to 10,000 committed
holy warriors.
In 629 AD, he marched on Mecca, the
legendary Haj, and seized the city with
ease. Within just 3 years, Muhammad had
seized the entire Arab Peninsula, an
expansion unlike any other in human
history. In 632 AD, just 61 years old,
Muhammad died of natural causes.
Following Muhammad's death, control of
the Islamic Caliphate fell to a series
of competent, ambitious rulers, the
Rashidadun or rightly guided.
In the very first year of their rule,
they launched an invasion, the Cisanian
Empire. Outnumbered 2:1, Muslim forces
dealt the Cisanians a crushing defeat at
the Battle of Chains in 633.
Before the Persians could react, the
Muslims had seized Mesopotamia.
When the Persians did regroup, they were
just as hopeless. No matter how
completely they outnumbered the Muslim
forces, the Holy Warriors simply
couldn't be defeated. By 642, the entire
Cisanian Empire had fallen to the
caliphate. Without hesitation, the
Muslims turned their attention to the
Eastern Roman Empire. They quickly
seized Syria and Egypt, then penetrated
deep into the hardland of Anatolia. The
Muslim armies were simply unstoppable.
Finally, in 656, they fell victim to
internal strife when the beloved califf
Uman was assassinated. [music]
The Muslim Empire was usurped by
Muhammad's cousin Ali. What ensued was a
schism which endures to this day. Shia
Muslims supporting Ali. Sunni Muslims
considering him a traitor. Just 5 years
later, Ali too was assassinated. The
Rashidun Caliphate tore itself to pieces
in civil war and ceased to exist. Yet
belief in Muhammad's teachings still ran
deep. Within a year, a new calip quickly
garnered support and united the empire
once more. The Umiad Caliphate was born.
Without delay, it resumed its
predecessors ravenous expansion.
Conquering North Africa with ease, they
encountered a new foe, the Christian
kingdoms of Europe. The Umiads were
undeterred. By 7-Eleven AD, they had
conquered the Iberian Peninsula,
overwhelming the fearsome Visigothths
and pushing them into France. The
caliphate now stretched from India to
Spain, one of history's greatest
empires. In just a few years, however,
Spain would be the entire extent of the
Umiad Caliphate. The bloated,
overextended empire would be decimated
by revolution.
>> [music]
>> In France, another revolution was taking
place. This time from within the palace
itself.
After gaining control of the Meravenian
dynasty in modern-day France, Charles
the Hammer established his bloodline
within royal power. By the time of his
death in 741, his grandson Charlemagne
was king of the Franks. Soon, the boy
would become much more. Charlemagne grew
up to be a military man, one of
history's finest. Throughout his 50-year
reign, his kingdom was never not at war.
He conquered the Saxons to the north and
the Lombards to the south, pushing into
the Kingdom of Italy. This brought him
into contact with Pope Leo III in Rome.
In the year 800, Leo asked Charlemagne
to visit Rome in order to mediate a
dispute. When Charlemagne arrived, the
Pope brought him before a massive
audience at St. Peter's Basilica. In a
complete surprise to everyone, including
Charlemagne himself, the Pope proclaimed
Charlemagne emperor of the West.
Like that, the Holy Roman Empire was
born. An emperor hadn't reigned in Rome
since Romulus Agugustus in 476,
and the people rejoiced.
Charlemagne continued his program of
aggressive expansion and ushered in an
age of cultural revival in the newly
founded empire. The Carolian
Renaissance, a period of intellectual
revival inspired by ancient Roman and
Christian culture. In this time they
made copying texts easier, preserved
classical works forming the basis of
modern Latin script. The lowercase
letters that we use today are derived
from what is called the Carolinian
minuscule which was developed [music]
during the reign of Charlemagne. In this
time works from Plato and Aristotle were
copied and preserved. Without Kyolian
scribes, many would have been lost
forever.
Massive cathedrals, [music]
immaculate illuminated manuscripts, a
ray of light in the dark ages of
medieval Europe.
>> [music]
>> On the opposite end of the world, China
was experiencing a golden age of its
own. For the first time ever, the Tang
Dynasty overhauled China's ancient rules
to create an efficient modern state.
Architectural wonders were constructed
on a scale never before seen. The
Lessian Giant, a massive Buddha carved
directly into a mountainside, was the
tallest statue in the [music] world for
more than a thousand years at 233 ft.
The Ting owe much of their success to a
usurper, an unexpected hero who seized
control of the Chinese throne for 45
years. Empress Wu, wife of the Tang
Emperor Gao Xang. Wu ruled in the
shadows for decades. Woos decrees became
more binding than the emperors, and in
690 AD, he formally relinquished the
throne to her. No one objected. In her
45-year reign, Wu expanded the empire
aggressively, conquering smaller
kingdoms to the east and extracting
tribute from Korea. China was once again
becoming a global power.
While the spoils of war poured in, the
empress cracked down hard on corruption,
ensuring wealth was used to improve the
military, support [music]
infrastructure, and finance the arts.
Her works would last forever.
Magnificent infrastructure such as the
Ming Tong and Tonong palaces still stand
tall. The halls are decorated with
murals, sculptures, dragons, and
Buddhist iconography.
The reformed Ting dynasty went on to
flourish for centuries.
Despite being overthrown, Wu became a
legend for the greatness she brought to
China. To this day, she remains the only
legitimate female ruler in the empire's
long history.
To the west there emerged in 600 AD a
fragile state surrounded on all sides by
superpowers that wished to destroy it.
The Empire of Tibet. Tibetan soldiers
are said to have covered their entire
bodies in exquisitly crafted chain armor
with holes only for their eyes. They
understood defense and survival. Thus,
the Tibetans protected in their mountain
fortresses resisted incursions from the
Tang, the Gupta, and perhaps the most
menacing, the Abbisids.
The Abbisids emerged as a radical
disciplined group within the
overextended Umiad Caliphate. When they
struck in 747 AD, the Umiads were
powerless to resist. By 750, the
Abbisids had seized [music] everything
but Spain. With three major powers all
close by, war was imminent in the year
751. The Tang were expanding west, the
Abbisids east. They met at Talis River,
the jurisdiction of the Tibetan Empire.
Seeking to first weaken the encroaching
Tang, the Tibetans sided with the
Muslims. Their combined forces totaled
200,000, the Tang 100,000, including a
contingent of Turkish slave soldiers, a
last resort. [music]
Yet, the Chinese had a secret weapon, a
military innovation, the crossbow.
Firing with extraordinary accuracy at
long range, Chinese crossbowmen
decimated the Arab infantry, nearly
causing a full-blown retreat. When the
Abbisid spearman did manage to get in
range of the Tang heavy infantry, they
found no luck. The Chinese were better
trained and better equipped.
Just when combat reached its most
heated, however, the Chinese were
undone. Their Turkish slave soldiers,
fearing death, rebelled and turned on
the Tang. [music] Their forces in
disarray, the Chinese scattered and were
dealt a crushing defeat. In the
aftermath, they withdrew east while the
Abassad forces were recalled to the
Levant to put down an uprising. One
power remained to seize the advantage,
the Tibetans. With the Chinese on the
back foot, Tibet launched an invasion of
Tang territory, seizing massive swaths
of territory in northern India. The
Tibetan Empire achieved its greatest
ever territorial extent in 754.
This would allow Tibet to negotiate the
Sino Tibet Peace Treaty on equal
footing, cementing its status as a
superpower equivalent to China for years
to come. The true victor in this
historic clash of global superpowers,
Tibet the middleman.
While Europe toiled in the dark ages,
soon the Abisid scholars would flourish
in philosophy, mathematics, [music] and
the natural sciences. In 762, they
founded a new capital in Mesopotamia,
the city of peace, the city of Baghdad.
Baghdad's legendary house of wisdom was
the medieval equivalent of the library
of Alexandria.
Its scholars ushered in the Islamic
Golden Age. Muslim scholars were masters
of translation. Positioned between the
eastern and western worlds, they had
access to both sides, an unrivaled
wealth of knowledge.
Not only did they invent algebra, house
of wisdom scholars invented numbers as
we know them today. By combining ancient
Hindu toms with contemporary
mathematics, they created something new,
the Arabic numeral [music] system. The
numbers 1 through 10 still use
throughout the world. Building on
ancient Greek principles, they invented
the spherical astrolab, allowing us to
track the stars with an incredible
accuracy.
These scholars discovered so many stars
that over 2/3 of the named stars to this
day have Arabic names.
Muslim scholars calculated planetary
movement with an accuracy unmatched in
Europe for another 500 years. In 964 AD,
they became the first in history to
identify the Andromeda galaxy, the
nearest major galaxy to the Milky Way
over 2.5 million lighty years away. The
scholar Al-Hazine is often called the
world's first scientist. He founded the
study of optics and is the first person
in history to correctly explain how
vision works by proposing that vision
occurs when light reflects from an
object and enters the eye and that the
visual image is formed in the brain. In
the 9th century AD, the Muslim scholar
Al Jahis published the book of animals
in which he identifies the struggle for
existence central to all living beings.
It would be an entire millennium before
this concept emerged in the west, though
with a different name, natural
selection, brought forth by Charles
Darwin. The House of Wisdom designed the
world's first programmable machine, a
self-playing flute powered by water,
which used a rotating cylinder with pegs
that could be repositioned to produce
different melodies.
They even created an early steam
turbine.
Europe toiled away in the dark ages
while scholars in the House of Wisdom
created the modern world.
Europe was plagued by a brutal primitive
menace, the Vikings.
Fierce seafarers from the rugged lands
of Scandinavia. [music]
Their society was tribal and honorbound
with loyalty to local chieftains and
kings. trumping any sense of national
unity. Viking children were raised in
this harsh world from an early age to be
tough, self-reliant, and skilled. Boys
were trained as warriors, sailors, and
hunters, learning to handle weapons by
the time they could carry them. Girls
learned to manage households and farms,
though they too were experienced to be
hardy and capable in the face of
hardship.
Viking fighting expertise was unmatched
in early medieval Europe. Vikings began
to appear on foreign shores. They soon
arrived in North Umbrea and raided the
island monastery of Lindesfarn in 793
AD. Monasteries were seen as sacred and
untouchable, making the attack a
terrifying sign of a new kind of enemy.
It was just the beginning.
Legendary warriors like Bjorn Ironside
raided such cultural centers as Paris,
Lisbon, and Galatia.
In 861, Bjornne reached Italy and sacked
Pisa. Marching his rugged band of Viking
soldiers north, Bujornne reached the
city of Looney and assumed it was Rome.
Unwilling to carry out a long siege, he
figured out another way to take the
city. He sent a message to the city's
bishop that Bujornne had died and in his
final moments had converted to
Christianity.
His last request was to be buried on
sacred ground. He then had his men put
him in a coffin. When the bishop granted
the request and took the coffin into the
city, [music] Bujornne jumped out and
began raising havoc, opening the city
gates and allowing his men to flood in.
The city was theirs. When Bjornne
realized that he hadn't taken Rome, he
consulted a shaman, one well-versed in
Norse mythology. He was told an
important tale. In order to bind the
mythical wolf, Finreer, the god Odin,
had to sacrifice his hand. Bjorn,
unwilling to make such a sacrifice, gave
up on conquering Rome. His expedition
was called off and he returned to
Denmark.
[music]
The city of Paris was surrounded by
wooden palisades and stone walls. Houses
were narrow and multi-storied. The
streets were crowded with merchants.
With Charlemagne's death, a decadesl
long inheritance struggle ravaged
Franchia. In 843, with the Treaty of
Verdon, the massive empire was divided
into three independent kingdoms. [music]
West Franchia, East Franchia, and
Loththeringia.
For centuries to come, these kingdoms
will battle fiercely amongst each other
to restore the total domination of
Europe their ancestors had once known.
Soon, they'd face competition from the
outskirts as well. The Bulgarian Empire,
the Serbian Empire, and the Duchy of
Croatia. Having shaken the Roman yoke,
they were developing into formidable
powers of their own and began expanding
aggressively. The lines drawn in 843
will endure and none would succeed in
uniting Europe.
This age also saw the peak of the Mayan
civilization in the land of modern-day
Mexico.
Their civilization had been slowly
advancing since the year 2000 BC. Their
crowning achievement, Chichin Ita, one
of the seven wonders of the new world.
At its height, the great city was the
largest and most diverse in Meso
America. Chichinita's very layout is a
testament to the gods. The entire city
is built around one great pyramid, El
Castillo.
As one of the most powerful cities in
Meso America, it was home to thousands
of people, [music]
including priests, warriors, craftsmen,
merchants, and farmers. The city bustled
with trade from as far as central Mexico
and the Caribbean.
Not only is El Castillo one of the most
massive monumental structures on the
continent, it is brilliantly aligned
with solar events. The Mayans gave the
Americas a calendar that predicts events
millions of years in the future. The
Mayans had an observatory known as El
Caracall. Its unique design includes
carefully aligned windows and doors that
allowed ancient astronomers to track
celestial events like solstesses,
[music] equinoxes, and the movements of
Venus. The Maya tracked Venus's 584day
sonotic cycle with incredible accuracy.
The Dresden CEX, a surviving Maya
manuscript, contains detailed Venus
tables that show their precision was
more accurate than contemporary European
astronomers.
The sacred city would dominate Meso
America for the next 300 years.
In 856 AD, an unknown Chinese monk and
alchemist was trying to invent a
substance that would heal ailments and
prolong one's lifespan. In doing so, he
mixed the following proportions. 75%
salt peter, 15% charcoal, and 10%
sulfur. [music] The result was
gunpowder.
The house they resided in was burnt to
the ground. Before long, the substance
would unleash chaos and destruction on
the world far beyond one simple house
fire.
It is the first great leap in military
technology since the discovery of
bronze.
First, it was used to create fire
arrows, then primitive rockets.
Soon, the Chinese were launching massive
gunpowder bombs at each other.
In addition to a far more discreet
invention, the fire lance, predecessor
[music] to the pistol,
the rest of the world wasted no time.
Soon, entire empires were being built on
gunpowder.
The Chinese word for gunpowder [music]
is still fire medicine, the name
assigned to it by the alchemist that
made the discovery. It serves as a
reminder that one of the most
devastating technologies in mankind's
history is the result of an effort to
discover life-saving medicines.
In 8:30 AD, a man named Dingga left his
home in Egypt to roam the plains of
North Africa. Finding the land barren,
Dingga is said to have struck a deal
with a snake god. If he sacrificed one
virgin each year, he would be blessed
with an endless supply of gold. Whether
by divine blessing or shrewd business
practice, Dingga flourished, acting as
an intermediary between Arab salt
traders in the north and gold miners in
the south, he made a killing. Before he
knew it, Dingga had created Africa's
first great trade empire, the Empire of
Ghana.
For centuries, visitors to Ghana,
including many scholars from Baghdad's
House of Wisdom, were astounded by the
extreme level of wealth on display. The
continent of Africa would soon see the
most wealthy civilizations and
individuals in history.
On the opposite end of the world, the
kingdoms of England would fight to their
dying breath to defend their kingdom.
When Alfred [music] the Great inherited
the throne of Wessex in 871 AD, the fate
of his homeland was already in jeopardy.
Having raided Europe for all it was
worth, the Vikings decided they would
settle down in the temperate British
Isles. The reigning Anglo-Saxon kings
could assimilate or be destroyed. Alfred
was still planning his father's funeral
when the Vikings struck, seizing a
massive swath of English territory. In
876, Alfred made peace with the Vikings,
exchanging hostages and a massive bribe.
It was short-lived.
The Vikings quickly slaughtered the
hostages they had been given and
attacked Alfred stronghold at
Chippenham. It was a massacre. Alfred
narrowly escaped. Fighting his way out
with a small band of loyal soldiers, he
retreated to a final stronghold in the
marshland.
His kingdom in shambles.
The Vikings turned their eyeire to the
remaining English kings. By 878, Wessex
was the only Anglo-Saxon kingdom that
hadn't fallen to the Vikings. For 6
months, Alfred remained in hiding. His
people believed him dead and their fate
sealed. When he emerged in May of 871,
the kingdom [music] rejoiced. He
summoned what remained of his men to
war, and they rode to meet the Viking
invaders. fighting for the survival of
their homeland. Alfred's makeshift army
dealt the Vikings a decisive victory at
the Battle of Edin, then another at
Rochester.
In 886, Alfred reclaimed the city of
London. He was no longer merely king of
Wessix, but the first king of the
Anglo-Saxons.
Alfred's grandson, Ethel Stan, would
deal the Vikings the final blow, driving
them out once and for all and becoming
the first king of a unified England.
[music]
It was not only the Islamic caliphates
threatening the survival of the
Byzantine Empire. They soon faced
invasion from a new empire arising in
the north, Kievan Rus.
Inhabiting the fertile lands surrounding
Kiev, the empire grew rich as a
Byzantine trading partner throughout the
800s AD. Before long, the barbarians
desired an empire of their own. In 882,
Roose was united under Oleg the Wise,
who immediately launched an ambitious
invasion, Constantinople itself. The
fierce Roose warrior struck like a
thunderbolt from heaven, brutally
dismembering anyone who stood in their
way. At the last minute, however, they
were turned away from the great capital
by a severe storm. In 941, Roose
returned with a fleet of 10,000 ships,
rampaging through the Byzantine
countryside and leaving entire cities in
ashes. Under Vladimir the Great, Roose
expanded to its greatest ever
territorial extent, reaching from the
Black Sea to the Baltic.
The barbarians were quickly becoming a
force capable of destroying the
Byzantines outright. Desperate, the
Byzantine Emperor Basil II turned to a
new method of defense. He sent in the
priests
and in 987 AD, Vladimir accepted
Christianity.
The very next year, he ordered the
entire city of Kiev to be baptized.
Byzantine priests baptized hundreds of
barbarians at a time, performing the
sacred ritual in lakes and seas.
Like that, Roose went from an
apocalyptic threat to one of the
Byzantine Empire's closest allies.
Having pacified Kievan Ruse, Byzantine
Emperor Basil II turned to another
long-standing foe in the north, the
Bulgarians.
Basil made it his life's goal to see the
Bulgarian Empire wiped off the map. At
the Battle of Clition in 1014, an entire
Bulgarian army was captured. In a brutal
display, Basil had 99 of every 100
soldiers blinded. The one left with
sight was left to lead his compatriots
home. The Bulgarians were no longer able
to resist Byzantine conquest, [music]
and Basil had earned a gruesome title
for himself. the Bulgar Slayer.
In the year 1250 AD, massive heads began
to appear on a small strip of land in
Polynia, Easter Island.
The Moai, massive stone sculptures, some
10 m tall and weighing more than 80
tons, constructed by the Rapanoui
people. Its purpose remains a mystery,
but the effort required was so
tremendous that it decimated the
island's ecosystem. 21 species were
driven into extinction.
By the time European colonists arrived
in 1722,
there were no more tall trees left on
the island with which to build canoes.
The indigenous population had shriveled
from 15,000 to 2,000 in just a century.
Of course, the arrival of Europeans
would bring only more destruction.
The Moai heads stand tall to this day,
but their creators would see a dramatic
collapse.
[music]
Along the southern coast of India, one
of history's great maritime empires was
emerging, the Chola. From 850 to 1050
AD, the Chola spread from India into
Myanmar, Malaysia, and Indonesia,
bringing order and vast wealth to the
land. The Cholan Navy is the most
dominant ever to emerge in India. They
controlled the lucrative movement of
goods by sea from China to the Western
world, establishing a naval equivalent
of the Silk Road.
Growing wealthy beyond imagination, the
Chola used their riches to build one of
Southeast Asia's [music]
greatest empires. In the capital, they
constructed elaborate tiered temples
still standing to this day. The Bria
Disa [music] Temple was built in 1010
AD. A massive tower standing 66 m tall
dedicated to Lord Shiva. The engineering
is so precise that the shadow of the
tower reportedly never falls on the
ground at noon.
To the south, the island of New Zealand
was settled by a much more fearsome
tribe in 1300 AD. The Maui, expert
hunters and tremendous warriors known
for expressive and menacing tribal war
dances. They found in New Zealand an
untouched island paradise. The land's
native species had never been hunted and
hence lacked necessary survival
instincts. What ensued was a massacre.
The moa, a 12 ft ostrich-like bird
numbered 2.5 million in New Zealand
before the Mauy arrived. Within 100
years, they were hunted into extinction.
The Mouri are some of humanity's most
accomplished explorers.
Voyaging south in their outrigger
canoes, they became the first humans to
discover Antarctica,
a place of bitter cold where rocklike
structures rose from a solid sea. The
Mouri are one of the most successful
tribal peoples at navigating European
contact. By selectively adopting and
rejecting certain European practices,
they endured [music] and still thrive to
this day.
While the Mauy were charting the icy
waters of the Antarctic, an explorer in
the north was making a similarly daring
journey. When Leaf Ericson was just 14
years old, his family was banished from
Iceland. His father, the renowned
explorer Eric the Red, decided to settle
in Greenland, establishing the island's
first permanent settlement in 982.
When he grew older, the ambitious Leaf
served in the court of the Norwegian
king, where he adopted Christianity.
Eager to return home to Greenland and
convert his family, Leaf's voyage was
blown off course by a storm. He washed
up on a rocky shore some 2,000 mi from
his destination. Emerging onto the
windswept island of Newfindland, Leaf
had just discovered a new continent.
He became the first European to set foot
on North America 500 years before the
voyages of Christopher Columbus.
[music]
Of course, North America's frigid,
barren Arctic had been inhabited for
millennia before the arrival of Leaf
Ericson. [music]
The Inuit people made a prosperous life
in one of Earth's most inhospitable
terrains. Agriculture being impossible
in the Arctic tundra, [music] the Inuit
exist almost solely on meat. They hunt
whales, seals, and even polar bears. By
consuming raw seal meat, they're able to
get the nutrition necessary for
survival. The wild, inhospitable land in
which they live gave birth to a unique
mythology among Inuit peoples. Inuit
belief holds that if you whistle at the
Aurora Borealis, the lights will descend
and cut off your head. The sun and moon,
however, share a deep celestial tale
blending family conflict, love, and
nature cycles. Anen, the moon spirit, is
in a never-ending chase of his sister,
the sun goddess Melina. After a violent
quarrel, she fled and he follows her
across the sky.
His pursuit [music] explains the moon's
phases. He forgets to eat during the
chase and grows thin only to return full
again.
At the heart of medieval Europe culture
were chivalry and feudalism.
The great majority of land belonged to
the king who allowed privileged noble
families to manage it for him, sparking
generations of dukes, counts and
vicounts. The land was in turn worked by
the surfs, the poorest of peasants bound
to the soil and belonging to their lord.
As the middle ages progressed, the surfs
came to massively outnumber the
landowning nobility throughout Europe.
The nobles needed protection from their
exploited surfs. To preserve the
feudalistic order, a warrior class
gradually emerged in Europe. Holy
knights bound to their noble lords.
Castles began to appear.
Initially made from wood and later
rebuilt with stone, castles served to
defend the king and those important to
the city. Often surrounded by a ditch or
moat to avoid attackers, castles
increasingly became larger in size and
would soon be each city's symbol of
power across [music] the lands.
In 1066, William the Bastard, Duke of
Normandy, invaded England.
At the legendary Battle of Hastings,
William's forces crushed those of Harold
Godwinson.
The Anglo-Saxons were driven out and the
Norman conquest of England completed.
[music] William the Bastard was renamed
William the Conqueror. Tales of his
conquest are immortalized in the Bayer
tapestry, an intricate illustration over
70 m long, showing each battle in vivid
detail and vibrant color. The fragile
tapestry has somehow survived over 900
years and is still preserved to this
day. To cement his rule, William
constructed castles throughout England,
including the legendary Tower of London,
a center of royal intrigue for centuries
to come.
In 1085, William embarked on the most
ambitious factf finding mission of his
time. A record of England so complete a
survey of this scale wouldn't be
completed again in the land for another
800 years. The Domes day book. It would
assess the land's wealth, assets, size
of estates, number of tenants, slaves,
animals, and farming equipment. At the
time, it asserted Norman control over
England, and how much tax could be
collected. It immediately earned William
a place as one of history's greatest
administrators.
In the Islamic world, the mad califf
al-Hakim was tightening his grip on the
holy land. One thing stood in his path
to absolute power. However,
Christianity.
Although al-Hakim ruled Jerusalem as
part of the caliphate, Christian
presence in the city had grown stronger
and stronger throughout the Middle Ages.
Each year, hundreds of thousands of
Christians would flock to the city in
pilgrimage. their destination, the
church of the holy sephiler,
Christianity's greatest holy site. Built
in the 300s AD, the Holy Sephiler was
constructed on the very ground where
Jesus was crucified. Many believed his
empty tomb was still housed in the
church walls. They traveled from the
opposite side of the earth to pay
respects to the sacred site. To all, it
was nothing but a bleeding ulcer. In a
shock to Christians all over the world,
in 1009 AD, Alhakim had the church of
the holy sephiler burned to the ground.
The tomb of Christ was destroyed,
reduced to rubble. Unbeknownst to all
Hakeim, he had just launched a new era
in humanity. When Christian backlash
came, it would be swift, fierce, and
bloody. The Crusades had just been born.
In 1,096 AD, the first crusade was
launched under the call deis vault.
God's will be done. Putting political
differences aside, soldiers were sent
from the many kingdoms of Europe and the
Byzantine Empire. First to strike was a
wave of poor European peasants stirred
into a fanatical frenzy by the
charismatic monk Peter the Hermit.
Before long, over 100,000 Christian
soldiers had rallied together and bore
down on Jerusalem.
The Knights of the First Crusade fought
with such vigor that rumors began
circulating throughout the Islamic
world. Perhaps these Christian soldiers
were indeed invincible.
By 1,099, they had seized a massive
swath of territory throughout the
Levant. The crusader states were born.
Most sacred was the newly founded
kingdom of Jerusalem. The church of the
holy sephiler was rebuilt and the
Christian world rejoiced. However, the
war was far from over. When the crusader
state of Adessa fell to Islamic forces
in 1146, a second crusade was launched
to reclaim the lost territory. It was a
complete disaster for the crusaders. A
hero emerged among the Islamic forces,
dealing the Christian invaders defeat
after defeat. Saladin, the man who began
as a mercenary and rose to become a
king. In 1187, having easily repelled
the second crusade, Saladin took
Jerusalem.
The crusader states were on the brink of
annihilation, and the Christians needed
a hero of their own. Two years later, he
emerged. Richard the Lionheart, King of
England.
Launching the Third Crusade, Richard
seized the city of Acre in 1191. He
pushed his forces inland where Solidan
lay in wait. At the Battle of Arsu, the
two legendary religious warriors met in
pitched [music] combat, each committing
their entire forces to the fry. The
winner would take all. Richard's forces
were outnumbered more than 2 to one. But
his discipline was legendary. [music]
Holding his cavalry back until the
perfect moment, the great general struck
with such brutal precision that
Saladin's forces were [music] routed
entirely. Richard restored the crusader
states, but conflict continued in the
region for centuries. Eventually, the
European kings were unable to maintain
the immense effort [music] required to
fight an overseas war. In 1291, the city
of Achre once again fell to Islamic
forces. There would be no effort to
reclaim it. The Crusades had come to an
end.
In Southeast Asia, the Kamir Empire
emerged from nothing to create the most
massive culturally complex empire the
region had ever known. During the reign
of King Surya Varmin II, the Kamir
Empire constructed the magnificent
Ankorwatt, a temple dedicated to the
Hindu god Vishnu. In Hinduism, Vishnu is
revered as the preserver and protector
of the universe. He is believed to have
10 avatars and is traditionally depicted
with blue skin holding four symbolic
objects. Approaching Ankorwat, one is
first met by an expansive moat and a
majestic entrance gate. The central
temple rises impressively resembling a
mountain. Its surfaces covered in
intricate carvings and stone reliefs
that narrate tales from Hindu mythology
and the legacy of the Kamir
civilization. Translating literally to
city of temples, Ankorwat is the largest
religious complex in the world over 400
square km in extent.
Its temples blend the styles of Hinduism
and Buddhism to create something unique,
intricate and breathtaking. To this day,
the national flag of Cambodia is a
depiction of the iconic temple.
Legend holds that Genghaskhan entered
the world clutching a blood clot in his
right hand. His beginnings were marked
by failure, hardship, and desperation.
The son of a Mongol chieftain, his
father traded him into servitude at just
8 years old to secure an alliance with a
neighboring clan. Just days later, his
father was betrayed, poisoned to death
by arrival. As his father's rightful
heir, Genghis spent the rest of his
youth taken prisoner by various
chieftains. In a series of daring
escapades, Genghis escaped their
clutches and made his way back to his
family. He joined the service of his
blood brother Jammuka who had risen to
become a chieftain. Together the two
brothers conquered the step bringing the
scattered Mongol tribes under a unified
banner. By 1206 [music]
they had united all the various tribes
uniting 1 million people. Fearing
Genghis's rise, Jammuka attempted to
have him imprisoned and executed. But
Genghis cheated death and escaped.
Assembling a coalition of Mongols,
Muslims, Christians, and Buddhists,
Genghis crushed his brother's armies in
a fierce three-day battle. Rule of the
Mongols was left to one man, Genghis
Khan. He was a progressive leader in
many ways. He made it illegal to sell
and kidnap women, banished the idea of
enslavement of any Mongol, and he was
welcoming of all religions, uniting the
people. However, he did not tolerate
rebellion. After defeating his enemies,
Genghask Khan was said to invite enemy
leaders to a banquet. And it is said he
crushed the enemy leaders beneath wooden
boards while he and his generals dined
to top them. This wasn't just a show of
power. It was humiliation, dominance,
and a message. No mercy for betrayal or
resistance. He expanded his empire's
borders with a vigor and brilliance
unrivaled in history. The kingdom
expanded to one of the largest and most
powerful the world had ever seen. In the
course of [music] the brutal campaign,
Genghis' forces killed more than 5
million, often putting entire cities to
death.
In 1227, Genghis died during a
successful campaign. His body was
transported back to Mongolia. And
according to legend, all the slaves who
conducted the funeral and constructed
his tomb, over 2,000 in number, were
forced to commit suicide in order to
preserve the secret. The tomb remains
undiscovered to [music] this day. At the
time of Genghaskhan's death, his empire
spanned an enormous expanse from the Sea
of Japan in the east to the Caspian Sea
in the west. Remarkably, nearly 8% of
men in Asia today can trace their
lineage back to him.
[music]
Emerging from the dark ages, the French
ruling dynasties found themselves
immensely wealthy and with regimes
stable enough to take on massive
multi-generational projects. The S
Chappelle Cathedral in Paris constructed
in 1248
with stunning vated ribbings and rich
stained glass that fills the peaked
arches. [music] The Gothic style is
born.
It didn't take long to spread throughout
Europe. Germany's Cologne Cathedral,
commissioned in 1248, wouldn't be
completed until 1880, an astonishing
600year construction.
Staggering in scale, the cathedral bears
the largest church facade known to man
and to this day is the [music] world's
tallest twin spire church. The Gothic
style wasn't limited to churches.
However, another class of construction
would begin to emerge, the university.
In 1088, the University of Bolognia in
Italy and in 1096, the University of
Oxford in England. Within these halls,
the groundwork was being laid for a new
age in Europe based on science and
reason.
While a new era dawned in Europe, the
Islamic world's golden age came to a
bloody end. The head of the opposite
caliphate, Al-Mustasim, refused to
submit to the everexpanding Mongol
Empire. Yet in a display of pure
arrogance, he also refused to summon
reinforcements to the capital of
Baghdad. What ensued was a massacre.
In 1258, the Mongol horde, numbering
over 300,000 men, tore down the walls of
Baghdad just a few days after their
arrival. They proceeded to ravage the
historic city for weeks on end, killing
as many as 2 million in the process. The
House of Wisdom for centuries, the
intellectual capital of the planet, was
burned to the ground.
So many manuscripts were thrown into the
Tigress River that the water ran black
with ink.
What deep ancient knowledge the Mongol
horde annihilated as it continued its
global rampage, we will never know.
Following the death of Genghask Khan,
the Mongol Empire was fractured by
internal rivalries. In 1259, it was
split into four competing empires. The
Golden Horde in Europe, the Chagatai in
the step, the Ilanate in Mesopotamia,
and the Yuan dynasty in China. Founded
by the legendary Kubla Khan, the Yuan
dynasty was the greatest of the Mongol
successor states, ruling all of
modern-day China and Mongolia. The Yuan
are the first foreign dynasty to conquer
the entire Chinese empire. Their
capital, modern-day Beijing, would
remain an industrial and cultural hub
for centuries. The Yuan were keen
patrons of the printing industry and
sponsored one of history's most iconic
writers, Marco Polo. Polo, initially
born in Venice, traveled to the court of
Kubla Khon as a merchant. When he
arrived, he was so impressed by the
emperor with his awe inspiring tales, he
was taken into the Yuan court and named
foreign governor. He and his men
flourished in the Yuan Empire for
decades.
When Polo finally returned to Venice
after 24 years, he was promptly arrested
by a rival republic. While in jail,
Marco met a fellow prisoner, Roollo
Depa, a writer of romances, where he
told him all of his stories. The result
was Roollo creating the famous book, The
Travels of Marco Polo. The book sparked
centuries of curiosity, showing the
Europeans for the first time the
greatness of the outside world. It
fueled the age of exploration.
Explorers like Christopher Columbus
carried a copy of the book with them.
Ironically, his arrest gave the world
one of the most influential travel books
in history.
[music]
In the 1200s, Japan was ruled by a
fearsome military dictatorship, the
Shogunate.
The class of warriors that dominated
Japanese society known as samurai valued
their honor above their lives. When the
Mongols sent a letter demanding
submission, the Japanese made no
response, but simply prepared to defend
their homeland.
In 1274, Kubla sent an invasion force
30,000 strong to capture Japan, but the
samurai easily repelled the disorganized
horde with the help of a severe storm
which cast the Mongol fleet off course.
7 years later, Kubla amassed another
invasion. This time, however, he would
spare no expense in dominating the
stubborn Japanese.
Sending 400 ships carrying over 150,000
men, the Mongol forces outnumbered the
Japanese 10 to one. Yet the samurai
refused to surrender. Defending the
coast in highwalled fortresses, they
kept the Mongols from disembarking. It
was a temporary measure, and the
decimation of Japan seemed inevitable.
Then fate intervened. A massive typhoon,
even more devastating than the first,
struck the Mongol ships yet again. Their
ships thrown to the rocks. Over 100,000
Mongol soldiers drowned or were killed
by the samurai. With their fleet
decimated, the Mongols would be unable
to launch another invasion. Japan became
one of the only kingdoms in the world to
fend off the Mongol horde. The fateful
typhoon was named Kamakazi, the divine
wind. The Yuan dynasty, meanwhile, fell
to pieces after the death of the great
Kubla Khan.
Monsum Musa ruled the most vast opulent
trade empire in Africa's long history,
the Empire of Mali. He spent his first
years as emperor in a constant state of
warfare with his neighbors. His goal
capture as many slaves as possible.
It seemed Monsamusa was building a slave
army, but to what end.
In 1324, it became clear. The emperor
was going on a pilgrimage and intended
to show the rest of the world just how
wealthy he really was.
Traveling 2700 miles from Mali to Mecca
in a sacred Islamic Haj, Monsamusa
brought over 12,000 slaves. Each one was
dressed in the finest silks and carried
4 lb of gold bars. A train of 80 camels
were laden down with 300 lb of gold
dust, which Musa gave to the poor along
the way. Every Friday, a holy day in
Islam, Mansam Musa built a new mosque so
he would have somewhere to pray along
the road. The Jinger mosque in Timbuktu,
built in 1327 under the commission of
Musa, reflects the wealth and Islamic
devotion of the Mali Empire during its
golden age. Monsam Musa's pilgrimage is
one of the most decadent displays of
wealth in history. Wherever the generous
man passed, he was remembered fondly as
the richest man in [music] the world.
The Islamic Golden Age was rapidly dying
in the east, and one last beacon still
stood in Muslim Spain, the Alhhamra
Palace.
The sprawling complex is one of the
greatest medieval achievements in
engineering. The means of accomplishing
this greatness, water.
Alhamdra's engineers were such advanced
hydraulic engineers, they were able to
give the palace heated floors, air
conditioning, and an ingenious reverse
well for driving water upwards.
At the heart of the palace, the central
fountain surrounded by 12 stone lions.
Not only a beautiful piece of
architecture, it also functioned as a
timekeeping device. By cleverly spacing
the outlets in the fountain space,
Alhhamra's engineers made it so that the
number of lions spewing water told the
hour of the day. When all 12 were
activated, the fountain's central spigot
would erupt and the clock would reset.
Alhamra would eventually fall to
Christian conquest. [music] Yet its
beauty and ingenuity were so astounding
that the palace was never sacked.
[music]
In Europe, conflict erupted in 1337.
Dynastic turmoil in France led the
English king Edward III to stake a claim
on the French throne, starting the H
100red Years War. In 1356, King John II
of France was captured by the English
after the disastrous battle of Puier.
And it looked like the conflict would be
brought to a quick and decisive end. But
John's son, Charles the Wise, would not
let go without a fight. Inheriting the
Kingdom of France, he reconquered every
inch of what the British had taken, and
the stalemate continued. Matters once
again turned in favor of the English
when Charles the Mad inherited the
French throne in 1368.
The Mad King suffered from constant
psychotic episodes.
At times he believed he was made of
glass, refusing to be touched.
He would have violent outbursts, even
killing his own soldiers accidentally.
At times he would even forget he was
king. It remains as one of the earliest
welldocumented cases of mental illness
in a European monarch. His reign
destabilized France to a breaking
[music] point. In 1429, however, a ray
of hope emerged which none could have
expected. A 17-year-old girl who had
received visions from God of a French
victory, Joan of Ark. The fierce young
woman entered the war just as the
English were about to seize Orleans.
Leading the French relief troops into
the fry, she broke the English siege and
chased them back to the Lir River,
regaining territory and restoring
crushed morale throughout France. Over
the next months, Jonavar would lead her
army to multiple victories.
During the siege of Compen in 1430,
however, disaster struck the French once
more. Jonavar was captured by the
English.
The young warrior stood stoically on
trial as she was found guilty of heresy
and witchcraft.
She was burned at the stake.
But the English had miscalculated. Joan
became a martyr to the French people,
more dangerous dead than alive. The
entire kingdom rallied to the cause. And
in 1453, [music]
they drove the English off the continent
once and for all.
After 116 years, Europe's first great
war was brought to an end.
In 1346, the most devastating epidemic
in human history struck the continent.
The bubanic plague, the Black Death,
brought from the step by the conquering
Mongols, the plague would go on to claim
200 million lives in just 7 years. 60%
of Europe's population would die. The
medieval world was left in shambles.
Seeking holy salvation, peasants huddled
together in churches praying. This only
helped the disease spread faster.
In the words of an Italian chronicler
living through the plague, none could be
found to bury the dead for money or
friendship. There was no one who wept
for any death, for all awaited death.
And so many died that all believed it
was the end of the world.
By 1375, the Aztec capital of Tenno
Tidlon was the largest and most powerful
city in Meso America.
Located on the once lake Tex Coco, the
city itself was most fascinating. It was
designed with a complex system of canals
and causeways to help control flooding
and facilitate transport across the
city. Here they crafted weapons of
unsurpassed devastation.
The Muawa Weedle, a long cudgel embedded
with obsidian blades sharper than a
razor's edge. By 1500, the Aztecs had
conquered all of Mexico and were
extracting tribute from Guatemala and El
Salvador.
Yet, the most notable aspect of Aztec
society, its brutality.
Death was an integral part of the Aztec
religion. The Aztecs believed that the
sun needed human blood to rise each day.
At their great temple in Tenno Titidlon,
over 20,000 lives were sacrificed each
year.
In some cases, the heart of the victim
was cut from their chest while still
beating. In others, the victim's flesh
was to be consumed by their family. For
the Aztecs, these atrocities were just
another part of everyday [music] life.
A young Vlad the Impaler became count of
the kingdom Wakia in 1448 in modern-day
Romania. In 1450, he was overthrown by
his brother-in-law with the help of the
Transians. When he reclaimed the throne
6 years later, there was one thing on
his mind, vengeance.
Brutally sacking the Transian villages
that had supported his rival, Vlad
rounded up everyone he could find and
brought them back to his castle in
Wleakia.
Unbelievably, 100,000 civilians were
impaled on wooden stakes and left to
die. Tales of Vlad's genocidal cruelties
have shocked generations. He's the
inspiration for a coldblooded, murderous
monster now known around the world, the
vampire Count Dracula.
However, to his own people and even
within modern-day Romania to this day,
Vlad was a hero. He was a brilliant
statesman, politician, and warrior
defending Christianity and his people.
The legendary walls of Constantinople
had repelled invaders for,00 years. When
the Ottomans invaded in 1453, the city
leaders didn't panic. They prepared for
a long and ultimately unsuccessful
siege. As always,
what they didn't account for, gunpowder.
The Ottomans brought with them the
Basilic, a gunpowder cannon weighing
18,000 kg, able to fire a half-tonon
cannonball 2 km away. The machine was
built for one purpose, to crush
Constantinople's legendary defenses.
The massive Basilic took hours on end to
reload, but each time it fired, the
impact was devastating.
After a month of unending bombardment,
the walls were rubble. The city was
ready to fall.
On May 29th, 1453, the Ottomans took
Constantinople.
The Byzantine Empire, the last vestage
of a once great Rome, was dead. A new
day dawned in the east with the Ottomans
supreme and untouchable. And yet, the
Byzantine legacy would live on.
Thousands of scholars fleeing the ruins
of Constantinople made their way to the
Italian kingdoms of Venice and Florence.
The knowledge and expertise they brought
with them triggered a new era in
European history. The death of the
medieval age, the Renaissance.
[music]
Though it began in Italy in the 1500s,
the innovations brought forth in the
Renaissance shaped all of Europe and
indeed the modern world.
A flurry of inventions created science
as we know it. The microscope allowed
scientists to understand life at a
fundamental level. While the telescope
advanced our understanding of the
universe we live in. The printing press
invented in Germany meant books and
newspapers no longer had to be printed
by hand. More and more people became
literate and began thinking critically,
eventually sparking revolutions
throughout the world. The nautical
compass will facilitate ambitious
voyages of discovery, opening up whole
new worlds of opportunity.
Perhaps most important, the steam
engine, generating massive amounts of
energy with negligible manual effort. It
would go on to revolutionize every
single aspect of industrial light. The
Renaissance was also a cultural
revolution.
In Florence, artists achieved complete
mastery of their crafts. Leonardo da
Vinci, in addition to countless
inventions, [music]
painted the Mona Lisa and the Last
Supper, pieces which remain unrivaled to
this day.
He was matched only by his contemporary
Michelangelo.
Although trained by Da Vinci,
Michelangelo was considered the superior
artist. His statue David is considered
the high point of sculpture while his
work on the ceiling of the cyine chapel
is perhaps [music]
the greatest artistic achievement in
human history.
In Florence, statecraftraft 2
flourished. Nicolo Mchavelli is one of,
if not the most influential pieces of
literature we have today. He invented
political science. The Prince is a
political manifesto that comments on the
past civilization we've heard about in
this video. The book set out rules for
the prototypical cutthroat modern
European ruler, giving rise to a system
of European diplomacy which will
dominate for centuries.
A new day was dawning in the West. The
Renaissance marks mankind's first steps
into the modern world.
It was the tiny kingdom of Portugal
which set the stage for European
conquest. Seizing land throughout the
African coast, they injected themselves
into the lucrative trade of gold and
slaves.
In 1488, they took it a step further.
Portuguese navigators rounded the Cape
of Good Hope, discovering the bustling
market on the Indian Ocean. Establishing
themselves as some of history's greatest
middlemen, the Portuguese merchants grew
immensely wealthy. First seizing trade
routes, then land itself.
Before they knew it, they had created
one of the largest empires in human
history, which would endure until the
year 1999.
Of course, the fate of the Western world
would not be decided in the Indian
Ocean, but the Atlantic.
>> [music]
>> In the bustling trade republic of
Genanoa, there emerged in 1451 a man
like no other. Christopher Columbus
began his career as an apprentice to a
wealthy goise [music] merchant. He
visited Ireland, England, even Iceland.
But still, the young man was unsatisfied
and his thirst for [music] adventure
only grew. When the Ottomans conquered
Constantinople, they barred Christian
merchants from accessing the lucrative
Silk Road. Europe was sent into an
economic tail spin and [music] searched
desperately for a new pathway to the
Asian markets. In 1492, Columbus met
with Queen Isabella of Castile and
proposed a solution. Seeking funding for
his next voyage, Columbus proposed
untold wealth, gold mines, valuable
[music] trade routes, and exotic goods.
He offered Spain a monopoly on western
access to Asia. He even asked for 10% of
the profits, a noble title, and
governorship of any lands he discovered.
A bold ask that showed his confidence.
The crown was drastically affected by
the recent wars. But Queen Isabella was
convinced and funded the voyage.
Columbus would cross the Atlantic as no
European had ever done, reaching the
east by sailing west. On October 11th,
1492, [music]
he reached the new world.
Completely unaware of the vast continent
stretching out before him, Columbus
reasoned he had in fact reached the East
Indies and hence called the native
people Indians, a term which endures to
this day. The Europeans had for the
first time arrived in the Americas.
His explorations marked a turning
[music] point in human history,
resulting in permanent contact between
the two hemispheres, marking the
beginning of globalization.
While Columbus would die believing he
had reached Asia, the rest of the
European world marveled at the new world
he had just mistakenly uncovered.
In 1497, a masterful Italian navigator
was employed by the British crown,
Javanni Kabato, John Kat. With a
skeleton crew of just 50 men, Kat sailed
the waters of the North Atlantic,
eventually landing on the island of
Newfoundland. Like that, he discovered
North America. Kat found the waters so
full of fish that his boats could
scarcely make it to shore. The British
eyed the rich waters eagerly and made
preparations for full-scale
colonization.
The race to conquer the wealthy new
world had begun.
Back in Europe, the Catholic Church was
not just a spiritual authority. It was
one of the richest, most powerful
institutions in Europe. However, thanks
to lavish spending, political wars, and
building projects like St. Peter's
Basilica, the church was drowning in
debt. To pay for it all, they turned to
a holy business venture selling tickets
to heaven. For a price, you could buy
your way into heaven. For a little more,
you could buy salvation for someone
already dead. Faith became a
transaction. One man decided to speak
out. His name was Martin Luther, a
German monk and scholar who believed the
church's practices went against the
Bible's teachings.
In protest, he wrote the 95 thesis, a
list of arguments challenging the
church's authority and calling for
reform.
He nailed them to the door of the
Wittenberg Castle Church, a call for
debate.
Instead, it sparked a revolution.
Thanks to the printing press, Luther's
ideas spread faster than the church
could contain them. First around
Germany, then throughout all of Europe.
On a continent of Catholicism, Martin
Luther sparked Protestantism. For the
first time, the Pope and church's
authority and traditions no longer held
unquestioned power over Christian belief
and practice. Protestantism focuses on
the Bible scripture alone as the
ultimate authority. Luther's movement
was beyond religious reform. [music] To
this day, in every protest, every
printed word, and every person who dares
to speak truth to power, the echoes of
Luther are present. His movement set the
foundations for democracy, the age of
enlightenment, and the American and
French revolutions.
Throughout the 1500s, the Spanish crown
sent in troops, the concistadors, to the
new lands of America. The most prolific
of their leaders, Hern and Cortez,
fighting the Aztecs for control of
Mexico.
Armed with guns, steel armor, and
oldworld diseases like smallpox, Cortez
and his concistadors were essentially
invincible.
Leading a retinue of only 500 men, he
cut through tens of thousands of Aztec
troops. The wy Spaniard would negotiate
alliances with rival tribes only to turn
around and massacre thousands of their
unarmed citizens when the tide of the
war turned. At his side, La Maline, an
Aztec slave given to Cortez as tribute.
Taking the woman as his lover, adviser,
and translator, Cortez was able to
commit complex deceptions against his
foe. In a matter of just a few years,
Cortez and his band brought the mighty
Aztec Empire to the brink of
annihilation.
Cortez may have held innumerable
military advantages over the tribal
Aztecs, but his forces remained
outnumbered 100,000 to1. He simply could
not take the Aztec capital of Tenno
Tidlon by direct attack. In 1519, an
alternative presented itself. The Aztec
Emperor Mcktazuma personally invited
Cortez into Tenno Titlon to negotiate.
Unbound by concepts of honor or truth,
Cortez promptly took the emperor
hostage, he used Mocktazuma as a
mouthpiece through which to rule the
empire while his men surreptitiously
slaughtered Aztec noblemen. The town's
people eventually rose up and stoned
their treacherous emperor to death, but
it was too late. The city was in
shambles, indefensible.
In 1521, Cortez delivered the final
blow, officially capturing the capital
and putting an end to the Aztec Empire.
Tennitlon was renamed Mexico City, the
colonial capital, which endures to this
day.
[music]
To the east, a different American empire
was about to face precisely the same
fate. From 1300 to 1500, the Inca built
a thriving metropolis in the mountains
of Peru.
Paved roads connected a network of
incredible cities from Kusco to Macho
Picchu, nestled in the Andes mountains
at an altitude of 2.5 km and beyond with
16 million citizens.
In 1524, the Spanish explorer Francisco
Pizarro arrived. Aruck at the wealth and
complexity of Inca civilization, Pizarro
wrote of the capital city, "It is the
greatest and finest ever seen in this
country or anywhere in the Indies. It
would be remarkable even in Spain." It
wasn't long before he decided to take it
for himself. As with the Aztecs, the
Inca were decimated by oldworld diseases
and unable to mount a defense against
Pizaro's superior technology.
12 million Inca were killed in just 50
years.
In 1570, the Spanish seized the
desiccated husk of a once great empire.
[music]
To the east, an empire continued to
flourish. Having conquered
Constantinople, the Ottomans continued
pushing west, capturing the Balkans and
parts of the step. By 1520, they had
annexed Egypt and the Levant. Under
Sullean the Magnificent, it expanded to
even greater heights, reaching its peak
in 1566.
The Ottomans controlled the Black Sea,
Dead Sea, and Red Sea, as well as
Mesopotamia and North Africa, becoming
the most powerful empire in the world.
Among history's greatest conquerors,
Sullean ruled more than 25 million
people.
Yet, the Sultan was also an avid scholar
and ruled through wisdom with religious
freedom. From Ukraine to Algeria, he
gained the loyalty of his subjects not
through fear, but through tolerance
[music] and order. On Sulleon's death,
the Ottoman Empire would fall to
infighting, and centuries of steady
decline followed. For 400 more years, it
endured, slowly becoming a relic of a
bygone age.
In England, an unhappy marriage was
about to lead to six centuries of
violent religious conflict.
Following his father's dying wish, Henry
VIII married Catherine of Aragon when he
inherited the throne. His regret was
immediate. To cope, Henry took countless
mistresses. But this wasn't enough. He
wanted someone new, someone with whom he
could conceive a legitimate heir. Yet,
the Pope refused to grant Henry an
anulment. So he took matters into his
own hands, banishing Catherine of Aragon
from his court, he married young Anne
Boland. [music] To get around the Pope's
objections, Henry passed the act of
supremacy in 1534, which declared that
the king, not the pope, was the supreme
head of the Church of England, leaving a
schism between the Church of England and
the Catholic Church even today. When
Catholic protesters arose, Henry simply
had them executed. When Anne Boland did
not give Henry a child, Henry simply had
her executed and took a new wife. In
total, Henry would take six wives before
his death in 1547. His quest for
domestic bliss left the kingdom in
shambles, and his incompetence triggered
a war with Scotland. For all his
efforts, Henry VIII's only legitimate
son would outlive him by merely three
weeks.
>> [music]
>> On the massive land of modern-day
Russia, there was not yet a unified
empire, but a patchwork [music] of
independent principalities slowly being
consolidated by the powerful state of
Moscow. In 1547, a young man named Ivan
IV became ruler and transformed Moscow
into a centralized Russian state. He
became the first Zar of a united Russia,
emperor of the lands. He was a brutal
leader. Anyone who questioned Ivan's
authority, whether the head of the
Russian church or a powerful general,
was put to death. He began a program of
cutthroat expansion from the Eural
Mountains to the Baltic Sea, bringing
Russia from a small duche to its hulking
present-day size. He turned Moscow into
[music] a true empire. His legendary
conquests gave him the title Ivan
Graznney, translating to Ivan the
Fearsome. His most notable depiction is
this painting, inspired by the event of
Ivan beating his own son to death. The
painting is widely regarded as one of
the most powerful depictions of regret,
guilt, [music] and human anguish in art
history. Ivan died with no heir left to
his throne.
The European Renaissance brought mankind
a new understanding of space. It began
with Nicholas Capernicus who in 1543
proposed the fundamental upheaval that
the earth revolved around the sun and
not the other way around. The theory was
expanded by Johannes Kepler who in6009
laid out specific mathematical rules for
how planets move through space. As
Kepler ingeniously calculated, planets
move not in circles but imperfect
ellipses. Galileo then provided
empirical evidence for these theories
with observations of Jupiter's four
moons, phases of Venus, and the rough
cratered surface of the moon. All of
which contradicted the geocentric model.
For his support of radical new
astronomy, he was nearly put to death by
the Catholic Church.
While astronomers explored the heavens,
old adventurers continue to chart the
new world. French settlers endured the
brutal northern winters to establish New
France in 1534, centered in modern-day
Quebec. King James I established the
first English colony in America at
Jamestown in6007.
The fertile soil soon drew countless
pilgrims. Before long, British North
America was thriving.
It wasn't long before the two
superpowers were racing to settle the
massive continent, sparking endless
conflict in the new world. In6009, the
Dutch entered the race, planting their
flag in what they called New Amsterdam,
the city now known as New York. They
would soon be driven out by the French
and English, and instead turned to Asia.
Here, the Dutch found that the
Portuguese had cornered the market.
However, they wasted no time in
undercutting Portuguese merchants,
building an empire for themselves. In
response, the Portuguese conquered the
sprawling territory of Brazil, where
Portuguese remains the national language
to this day. The resourcerich land would
prop up the Portuguese Empire for
centuries to come. The Spanish expanded
their Mexican territory into modern-day
Florida and California. When the
legendary explorer Mellin discovered a
route to Asia through the Pacific, Spain
also conquered the Philippines.
With all the world stretched out before
the European kingdoms, they went into a
frenzy and fought bitterly for a place
at the top of this new world order.
Not all colonial expeditions promised
[music] success. In6006, a Dutch
merchant arrived in Australia, seeking
the next breakthrough discovery. Before
he had even reached the shore, he found
himself under fierce assault from
indigenous warriors on the shore,
littering his ships with arrows. Several
of his crewmen were killed, the rest in
utter panic. The merchant retreated. He
named Australia New Holland and went
home, never to return.
Australia's land was unlike any other.
Aboriginal Australians mastered one of
the world's harshest landscapes for over
40,000 years. They were hunter gatherers
with hundreds of tribes spread across
the continent. Their food selection was
unlike any other culture on Earth. They
hunted and cooked kangaroos and emus.
Their weapons were even more unique. For
example, the boomerang, a curved
aerodynamic tool that when thrown
correctly will fly in a curved path and
return to the thrower.
Traditional instruments like the digery
have become prolific cultural touchston
known throughout the world. To navigate
the lands, they used songs passed
through generations, each containing
encoded maps, environmental cues, sacred
knowledge, and survival wisdom. For tens
of thousands of years, the Aboriginals
[music] thrived in harmony with the
land. But in 17th century England, one
man dared to disturb nature, not with
fire or spear, but with mathematics
[music] and thought.
Sir Isaac Newton is one of history's
greatest geniuses and one of its
strangest. Whilst attending university
in Cambridge, the bubanic plague had
resurfaced and the young Newton was
forced to move to the countryside. It
was here he worked alone for the next 2
years. There's a famous story of an
apple falling on Isaac's head causing
him to question gravity. However, this
story is just a myth, though the true
story is not far off. Newton told
biographers that he had seen an apple
fall from a tree while sitting in a
garden. This moment made him wonder, why
do apples always fall straight down? Why
not sideways or [music] upward? That
simple question led him to think deeper
about gravity, not just on Earth, but in
the sky. He connected the falling apple
with the moon staying in orbit, both
caused by the same force. He discovered
the laws of gravity.
He then discovered the laws of motion.
He was asked, "Why do the planets orbit
in ellipses rather than a perfect
circle?" To find his answer, he had to
utilize a whole new form of mathematics.
He created calculus.
It would go on to help humans build,
explore, cure, predict, and understand
the world in ways we never could before.
To this day, bridges, airplanes, phones,
and rockets are still created using
Newton's mathematics.
Soon, Isaac Newton's discoveries would
challenge further than just the academic
world.
Since ancient times, it was believed
white light was pure and colors were
impurities.
Newton discovered the opposite. White is
made up of all the colors of the
rainbow. He proved this by using a
prism. [music] White light goes in,
splits into red, orange, yellow, green,
blue, indigo, violet. Then he took those
colors and passed them through another
prism. They turned back into white
light. This shocked the scientific and
artistic world. He discovered the laws
of optics which helped scientists
understand how light travels, bends, and
splits.
This knowledge allowed for the precise
design of lenses for glasses,
telescopes, microscopes, and cameras.
Isaac Newton does all of this, then
turns just 26 years old. Almost 20 years
later, he would go on to publish his
greatest masterpiece, Principia,
explaining not just falling apples and
orbiting planets, but the motion of
everything in the universe. It became
one of the most important scientific
works in history, marking the birth of
classical physics.
Over in India, the Mughals had conquered
the entire subcontinent of India. They
gave the world one of the most iconic
pieces of architecture ever created, the
Taj Mahal.
It was built by the king Sha Jan in
honor of his wife. As a teenager, the
king fell in love with a Mumage Mahal.
Together, they had 14 children, but
Mumage Mahal tragically died from birth
complications during the last one in
[music] 1631.
At her death, Sha Jan was so distraught
that he paid the modern equivalent of $1
billion to have the mausoleum
constructed for her. When he died 30
years later, he too was interred there.
At the center of the sprawling Taj Mahal
lies the tomb of two lovers, visited by
millions each year, their love forever
immortalized in history.
Following the French and Indian War, the
British controlled all of colonial North
America. The Spanish were driven back to
Mexico and the French routed from the
continent entirely. The legendary 13
colonies thrived and were quickly
becoming the world's dominant economic
powerhouse.
The availability of natural resources
was staggering. Indigenous peoples were
slaughtered, enslaved, and decimated by
diseases. Their land was seized, further
enriching the colonies.
Most crucial to American success,
however, was the transatlantic slave
trade. The triangular trade, raw
materials are taken from the Americas to
Britain, where they're used to
manufacture goods. The finished goods
are taken to Africa, where they're
traded for slaves. The slaves are taken
to America where they're used to harvest
raw materials. And so the cycle
continues.
Human beings were treated as cargo
packed below decks so tightly that they
couldn't move. 15 million slaves were
shipped this way in total. 1/5if of them
died on the voyage. The practice of
slavery would go on to rend the American
nation in two. First, however, it had to
become a nation. The 13 colonies were
still British colonies. By the 1770s,
cries for change were becoming too loud
[music] to ignore.
In 1707, England, Wales, and Scotland
ratified the Acts of Union and
officially became one, the Kingdom of
Great Britain. The unified block turned
its gaze outward. Before long, it would
form the basis for the British Empire,
the largest ever known to man. To build
an empire, the British would need bold
explorers. Among these was Captain James
Cook. Cook went on to chart vast regions
of the untamed North, creating maps of
Canada, which would be used for more
than 200 years. He then led the crews of
the HMS Endeavor to the Pacific,
becoming the first European to circumn
New Zealand and the first to communicate
with the fearsome Maui. [music]
In 1770, he became the first European
ever to set foot on the vast continent
of Australia, establishing a fort at
Cape [music] York, Cook began the long
process of settlement which would
culminate the Australia we know today.
He then became the first to cross the
Antarctic Circle in 1773.
The Lords of England tried to persuade
the man to return home and settle,
honoring him with countless awards,
including the title the first navigator
in Europe. But Cook simply couldn't
resist the call to adventure. In 1776,
he returned to sea, becoming the first
to chart the northwest coast of America.
He then discovered the Hawaiian Islands
where he was welcomed by the indigenous
peoples as a [music] god.
His crew was not treated quite so
warmly. However,
when a dispute with the indigenous
people turned violent, Cook took a
Hawaiian king hostage and attempted to
flee. The villagers gave [music] chase,
clubbed Cook on the head, and stabbed
him to death. In the end, gave his life
to the pursuit.
Few
prodigies throughout history can rival
the absolute mastery Isaac Newton had
[music] in his field. Wolf Gang Amadeus
Mosart is one of them.
He composed his first known piece of
music at the age of five and traveled
throughout Europe seeking ultimate
inspiration.
At just 14 years old, while in Rome
during Holy Week, he attended a famous
performance of Allegri's Miseri in the
Syine Chapel, a piece that was strictly
forbidden to be copied or performed
outside the Vatican. After hearing the
Miseri only once, Mosart wrote it down
entirely from memory, accurately
reproducing it. This act amazed many, as
the piece had been kept a secret for
over a century. Instead of punishing
him, Pope Clement I 14th summoned
Mosart, praised his genius, and even
awarded him the Order of the Golden
Spur, a papal knighthood. Across his
lifetime of just 35 years, he composed
over 800 pieces. As the young man grew
progressively more ill, he began
composing the Reququum, his magnumopus.
During the process, he struggled to eat,
move, and even talk. and still from his
bed he continued composing. Mozart
intended the reququum to be played at
his own funeral. He died in 1791 before
the piece was completed.
However, the world now knows the tomb.
The over 200year-old masterpiece is
still used in modern-day movies and
still fills concert halls all around the
world.
In the prosperous 13 colonies, trouble
was brewing.
American colonists were being taxed the
same as British citizens or more, but
had no say in governmental affairs. In
the 1770s, they began to revolt. At the
Boston Tea Party in 1773, a group of
dissatisfied Americans raided a British
merchant vessel and dumped a modern
equivalent of 1.7 million worth of tea
into Boston Harbor.
The Patriot Movement was born, violently
demanding independence.
Two years later, the Boston rebels
engaged the British in the field,
scoring a miraculous victory in the
battles of Lexington and Concord.
If they were going to stand any chance
against the full force of the British
Empire, the Patriots would need
leadership.
In 1775,
it arrived General George Washington.
Taking command, Washington turned the
American Revolution from a series of
disorganized skirmishes into [music] a
full-blooded war. The half-hazard
patriot movement became the Continental
Army and Washington its
commander-in-chief. Washington's
greatest skill as a general quickly
became clear. He knew how to properly
lose a battle. At Long Island, Brandy
Wine, and German Town, his forces were
utterly crushed by the British.
But each time, the general somehow found
a way to escape with enough strength to
fight another day. He saw the big
picture. Washington was fighting a war.
While Washington continued to stump the
British, his compatriots were
nationbuilding. On July 4th, 1776, the
Declaration of Independence was
ratified. The 13 colonies became the
United States of America, an
independent, self-governing nation.
Months later, Washington spontaneously
crossed the Delaware River, shocking the
British forces, dealing them defeat
after defeat, Washington drove the
British to their final stronghold at
Yorktown. In 1781, they finally
surrendered. One [music] of the most
important revolutions in the history of
mankind came to a successful end. The
world's next great superpower was born
and George Washington would refuse to be
king. Instead, leading the nation as the
first president.
Great Britain's loss of 13 American
colonies was a severe blow to the
empire. The British crown had shifted
its gaze to the rest of the globe where
vicious imperialism thrived. In 1788,
the British established the colony of
New South Wales, an island of exile for
the worst English criminals, which would
later become Australia.
In India, British economic domination
became direct political control with the
establishment of the Raj.
While in Meso America, new British slave
colonies were established. In the north,
they kept their grip on the massive
colony of Canada in spite of American
independence.
The British were on the path to global
mastery, but they weren't without
competition. The Portuguese expanded the
massive territory of Brazil in 1777,
coming to dominate South America. While
they were ousted by the Dutch in Asia,
they made headway throughout Africa in
such wealthy provinces as Mosamb beek
and Angola.
The Dutch controlled the East Indies
with their colonies of Indonesia and
Malaysia.
Dutch expansion into South Africa would
soon spark conflict with the British and
Portuguese.
The Americans expanded their borders
under what they called manifest destiny,
granting themselves the right to conquer
the entire continent. In 1803, they
purchased the massive territory of
Louisiana from the French, who began to
forsake overseas acquisitions. Instead,
they conquered that which lay directly
before them. By 1812, almost all of
Europe found itself under French rule.
Not the French Republic, but the first
French Empire.
The success of the Americans in building
a republic led France, the most powerful
kingdom in Europe, to contemplate the
state of their own government. At the
time the French were ruled by King Louis
V 18th and his wife Queen Marie
Antuinette. Whilst the peasants [music]
starved the monarchs lived in absolute
luxury. The French commoners had enough.
They decided they wanted more say in how
the country was run and they formed a
group called the National Assembly and
started making new laws to give them
more rights. Armed with pitchforks and
musketss, they stormed the Bastile,
France's prison that represented the
king's power. The French Revolution had
begun. Headed by Maximleian Robes
Pierre, the symbol of the revolution was
created, the Madame Guillotine, an
invention meant to make execution quick
and humane in the crowded squares of
Paris. It claimed more than 15,000
lives, eventually even beheading the
king and queen themselves. After the
people of France voted in Maxmleonian
Robes Pierre. However, in a twist of
fate, Robes Pierre became known as a
ruthless and uncompromising figure. Soon
thousands of people were arrested, tried
[music] and executed for crimes against
the revolution. The people grew tired of
the violence. The French had revolted
once before and would do so again
against the man they once called a hero.
Ironically, [music] Robes Pierre was
taken to the guillotine and executed.
The French Revolution forever
transformed France, laying the
foundation for democracy, individual
rights, and the end of absolute
monarchy.
Napoleon Bonapart was born in a small
unimportant French colony off the coast
of Italy. Yet the young man's ambition
knew no bounds. Serving in the French
Revolution army, he saved the fragile
republic from its countless enemies time
after time and quickly became France's
most powerful general and a beloved
national hero. In exchange for his
heroism, Napoleon made one simple
demand, absolute dictatorial power.
In 1804, he was named the first ever
emperor of the French. He crushed the
Holy Roman Empire, the Prussians, the
Russians, and the Spanish. Napoleon was
unstoppable.
Not only was he an indisputable military
genius, Napoleon poured his blood,
sweat, and tears into the empire.
Whether at home or on campaign, he
worked 16 hours every day almost without
pause. For a time, it seemed he might
conquer the world.
In 1812, however, at the height of his
power, Napoleon made a fatal flaw. He
launched a full-scale land invasion of
Russia. [music] The Russians adopted
their legendary scorched earth policy,
which had stopped invaders since [music]
Genghask Khan. Napoleon's men were
decimated by cold and starvation in the
brutal Russian winter.
He marched in with 600,000 troops in
1812 and limped out 2 years later with
70,000.
The European powers seized the
opportunity to rise up and crushed what
remained of Napoleon's forces, sending
him into exile in 1814.
The irrepressible general returned to
France the very next year, however,
rallying an army of 300,000 to his
banner. In the legendary 100 days, he
inflicted several crushing defeats to
the Allied European powers. And for a
moment, it looked as though he might
reclaim his empire. Yet at the Battle of
Waterlue on June 18th, 1815, he was
unable to defeat the English general
Wellington. Napoleon was once more sent
into exile. This time deep in the
Atlantic where he could never escape.
The great general died in exile and the
short-lived French Empire came to an
end.
[music]
A new age was upon humanity. The
industrial revolution. It began in
England, where inventions like the
spinning jenny fundamentally overhauled
manufacturing throughout the 1700s.
Processes that had been done by hand for
millennia were now automated,
eliminating the need for costly
employees. The invention of the steam
engine took these automatons to an
unprecedented scale, mankind's first
factories.
It also led to a revolution in transit.
Horses were replaced by automobiles and
massive freight trains. It didn't take
long for the rest of the world to follow
England's example. Europe, Japan, the
United States, economies were rebuilt
from the ground up, centered on
automation and cutthroat capitalism. The
modern world was born.
The industrial revolution wasn't without
its flaws. Increased production meant
higher demand for raw materials like
cotton, leading to a [music] massive
expansion of American slavery.
While factory owners and early investors
grew unthinkably wealthy, the poor
stayed poor and even children were
forced to endure deplorable working
conditions in early factories. By the
1800s, war was brewing, not between
nations, but between [music] classes.
Among those horrified by England's
industrial revolution was a young writer
named Carl Marx. Markx moved from
Germany to England in 1849 to witness
the birthplace of industry firsthand.
[music] It was here that he composed his
magnumopus dos capital.
Over 3,000 pages in length, dos capital
remains one of the most compelling,
comprehensive works of philosophy ever
composed. It frames all of human history
as a war between classes. The working
class, called the proletariat, is
consistently [music] exploited by the
bgeoa, the businessowning elite. Markx
called for a global revolution, the
replacement of unjust capitalism with
communism, where [music] all people are
equal and deserve equal rights and
opportunities.
Soon it inspired violent revolutions
across the world and centuries of
ideological warfare.
As the 19th century began, one of
history's great superpowers found itself
spiraling into ruin. China's century of
humiliation,
beginning with the infamous Opium Wars.
For decades, the British had made
immense profits smuggling [music] opium
into China through Turkey. In 1832
alone, the East India Company sold more
than 2,500 tons of the illegal
substance. Opium addiction became the
biggest public health crisis facing the
Chinese Empire. However, when the
Chinese government cracked down on the
opium trade in 1840, the British
intervened for weeks on end. The
superior British fleet bombarded Chinese
ports until China was forced to
surrender. The terms of peace were
crushing.
The British seized the city of Hong
Kong, which would remain a British
colony until 1997.
The Chinese government was also forced
to open its borders to the opium trade
and worst of all was forced to pay
reparations for the financial damages
they had done to British opium dealers.
In today's currency, the reparations
paid exceed $1 billion.
In the wake of the humiliating defeat,
the Chinese government began to lose
control of its people. The land was ripe
for revolution.
In 1850, it finally came. The Taiping
Rebellion, the bloodiest revolution in
history and one of the strangest. The
rebel leader Hunguan proclaimed himself
to be the brother of Jesus Christ. He
declared a new religious state in
Eastern China, the Heavenly Kingdom, and
with his zealous legions soon ruled over
more than 30 million citizens. The
central Chinese government would
eventually put down the Taiping
Rebellion, but at a cost. 14 years and
more than 20 million dead. China was
utterly devastated. And as the modern
age began, it was nothing but rubble.
The United States, meanwhile, faced
civil strife of its own.
Having expanded their borders from coast
to coast, a clear division had emerged
in the nation. The north was
industrialized, coming to adopt liberal
values in massive cultural centers like
New York City. The southern states, on
the other hand, were agrarian. They made
their money harvesting natural resources
on the backs of slaves.
Slavery had been abolished in much of
the Western world by the early 1800s.
Before long, the moral crisis began to
plague the educated north. A politician
rose through the ranks giving voice to
the abolitionist movement, Abraham
Lincoln. When Lincoln was elected
president in 1860, the southern states
were so outraged that they declared
themselves independent and attacked the
North. The American Civil War had begun.
The fighting was bloody with more than 1
million lives claimed. But in the end,
the industrialized North triumphed
decisively.
In 1865, the USA was reunified.
In his legendary Emancipation
Proclamation, Lincoln abolished slavery
in the United States, a massive leap
forward on the path to equality.
But the war had taken a toll on Abraham
Lincoln, and for him, things would only
get worse.
Just 5 days after bringing an end to the
Civil War, Abraham Lincoln was
assassinated.
His nation would live on thanks to his
tremendous effort.
Although the slave trade was coming to
an end in the 1800s, Western imperialism
was experiencing a golden age. The most
contested colonial prize, Africa. In
1870, 10% of Africa was under colonial
control. By 1914,
90% of the continent had been seized.
The Western European powers fought
bitterly to take more of the continent,
giving rise to the so-called scramble
for Africa. While the French reigned
supreme in the north, holding colonies
like Morocco and Tunisia into the late
1900s, the British and Belgians competed
for the south. In the Congo, Belgian
colonists went to such brutal extremes
to harvest ivory and rubber that 75% of
the Congalles population was wiped out.
12 million lives in just 20 years.
In Liberia, on the other hand, fierce
independence reigned. Since 1822, freed
slaves from the USA had been migrating
steadily to Liberia. They sought to
build a new society in the homeland from
which their ancestors had been
kidnapped. In 1842, the settlers of
Liberia issued a declaration of
independence, becoming a nation of their
own, independent of American
imperialism.
Entering the scramble for Africa late
was the naent German Empire which only
unified in 1871 and still struggled to
be recognized as a global superpower.
Soon this struggle would turn violent. A
new age of global conflict loomed on the
horizon.
By 1914, Europe was on the brink of
destruction. It began with nationalism.
Great Britain resented the meteoric rise
of the Germans, who were building an
empire of their own and surpassing the
British in naval might. To keep Germany
in check, the British allied with the
French monarchy, the Russian Empire, and
the Kingdom of Serbia. Germany then
formed an alliance of its own with the
Kingdom of Italy, the decaying Ottoman
Empire, and the Austrians.
The fuse was set. All that was missing
was a spark. On June 28th, 1914, a
Serbian citizen assassinated the heir to
the Austrian throne. The Austrians
declared war on Serbia. Both alliances
were automatically dragged in and Europe
found itself [music] at war.
For the first time ever, the world saw
modern industrialized warfare.
Airplanes, tanks, [music] submarines,
machine guns, poison gas, and even
flamethrowers became tools of mass
death. Four years later, 22 million lay
dead. Having lost the war, Germany was
forced to take the entire blame for its
outbreak and to pay crushing
reparations. France was utterly
decimated economically and terrified of
another German invasion. In Russia, the
Revolutionary Communist Party seized
control in 1917, murdering the royal
family. The Bolsheviks abolished the
monarchy and created what would soon
become the Soviet Union.
The European psyche was scarred.
Modern art emerged to express the
fundamental horror everyone was feeling.
Strange abstract pieces like Picasso's
Gerna. The modern world would never be
the same.
The early 1900s became a golden age of
genius. Not only for death and
destruction, Nicola Tesla was an
inventor like no other. He dreamed of
giving the world free wireless
electricity. He created the Tesla coil,
unlocked the power of alternating
current AC, and imagined things far
beyond his time. From remote controls to
wireless communication,
Thomas Edison, Tesla's rival, gave the
world the electric light bulb
and recorded sound for the first time.
He held over 1,000 patents and helped
bring [music] electricity, movies, and
recorded music to everyday life.
Marie Cury became the first woman to win
a Nobel Prize and the only person to
ever win in two different sciences. Her
discoveries in radioactivity changed
medicine forever, allowing us to fight
cancer with radiation. She worked so
intensely with radioactive materials,
her notebooks are still dangerous to
touch.
Albert Einstein changed the universe
with a single equation. E= MC^².
It showed that mass and energy are the
same thing and opened the door to
nuclear power. He discovered that time
and space bend with gravity.
Neils Boore helped make sense of it all.
He built the model of the atom with
electrons in orbits. His work helped
launch quantum mechanics, the theory
behind modern computers, lasers, and
nuclear power.
Whilst these geniuses achieved in the
name of science and development, their
discoveries would play a major part in
the most deadly war in history just
years later.
The most brutally effective dictator of
the 1900s and perhaps of all human
history was Adolf Hitler.
Rising up from the gutters of postwar
Germany, Hitler rallied the entire
nation behind his cause, the Nazi party,
the revitalized German Empire began
conquering Europe. In 1939, they invaded
Poland and the world once again went to
war.
85 [music] million people died in the
Second World War. It remains the
deadliest conflict in human history. An
unimaginable toll which cannot be put
into words.
In 1945, Nazi Germany was overrun by a
joint invasion of the Allied forces from
the west and Russians from the east.
Hitler committed suicide.
In the east, however, Germany's ally
Japan refused to surrender. It would
take a new military innovation, one of
pure devastation, to change their mind.
The nuclear bomb dropped on Hiroshima
and Nagasaki in August 1945.
>> The Second World War was finally over,
having [music] brought humanity to the
brink of annihilation.
The demonstration of nuclear power
changed things. With the threat of a
global nuclear holocaust now present,
world peace was no longer optional,
nations throughout the world gained
independence. In India, Gandhi's method
of peaceful protest defeated the British
Raj. While in South Africa, Nelson
Mandela employed a violent rebellion to
attain independence. China was ravaged
by a bloody civil war culminating in a
victory by the communists in 1949.
The world was quickly dividing into two
camps. The capitalist west headed by the
USA against the communist east headed by
Russia.
From 1945 to 1989, Russia and the US
vied bitterly to prove who was better.
This was primarily fought in a new
uncharted arena, outer space.
In 1957, the Russians launched Sputnik,
the first satellite to reach outer
space. In 1969, the Americans traveled
to the moon. The spirit of competition
which pervaded the space race led to a
global technological revolution. The
computer, the wireless phone, the
internet.
Although not all revolutions were about
technology,
the next generation of women across the
world would rise up, organizing
protests, breaking barriers, and
demanding equal rights and
representation despite fierce opposition
and societal push back. By the end of
the century, women had firmly
established themselves across all
sectors of society.
Similar movements regarding racism and
civil rights would take strides with
prominent figures from across the world
like [music] Martin Luther King Jr. and
Nelson Mandela fighting for equality. By
the century's close, a growing global
movement toward human rights and social
justice was more widespread than ever
before.
>> [music]
>> It is safer to be alive today than in
any period [music] of history ever. With
a population of over 8 billion people
and over 5 billion internet users, the
world has never been more connected than
it is now. In 2007, [music] Steve Jobs
would step up onto the stage and unveil
a device that would redefine humanity,
the iPhone.
This moment marked the dawn of the
smartphone era. Life itself would be
reconstructed around these handheld
devices. Social media, entertainment,
real-time navigation, remote working,
video calls, and even the beginning of
artificial intelligence.
And so, here we are. As the Athenian
historian Thusidities said over 2,000
years ago, "History is philosophy
teaching by examples." In today's age of
unprecedented access to short-term
satisfaction, history reminds us of the
long-term consequences.
Humankind has massive potential and
equally massive responsibility. [music]
From the cities of Sumeriia to the
Egyptian pyramids, from the Colosseum to
the Great Wall of China, from the Taj
Mahal to the countless skyscrapers of
today, given another 10,000 years to
wander the earth, there's no telling
[music] what human civilization will
become.
>> [music]
>> Heat.
[music]
Heat.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Heat. Heat.
>> [music]
[music]
>> Heat. Heat.
Heat. Heat.
Heat.
[music]
Heat. Heat.
Heat.
[music]
Heat. [music]
Heat. Heat.
[music]
Heat. Heat. [music]
>> [music]
[music]
>> Heat. Heat.
Heat. Heat.